<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: d3 | The Conscientious Programmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/categories/d3/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-08T02:38:11-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Franklin Chen]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[franklinchen@franklinchen.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pittsburgh Code and Supply: Programming in journalism]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2014/07/17/pittsburgh-code-and-supply-programming-in-journalism/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-17T21:21:19-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2014/07/17/pittsburgh-code-and-supply-programming-in-journalism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://static.squarespace.com/static/538f3cc8e4b00f52172b5560/t/53a4ec76e4b0488fb14c5a29/1403317372203/sign.png?format=500w">http://static.squarespace.com/static/538f3cc8e4b00f52172b5560/t/53a4ec76e4b0488fb14c5a29/1403317372203/sign.png?format=500w</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>I finally attended my first ever <a href="http://www.codeandsupply.co/">Pittsburgh Code and Supply</a> meeting! The group, which posts its <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/">events on Meetup</a>, was created by local Pittsburgh software developer <a href="https://twitter.com/justinxreese">Justin Reese</a> just a few months ago, in March 2014. His vision is to create a local community that, unlike conventional specific language/technology-based meetups, is much more universal and broad. If you haven&rsquo;t do so already, read more about the <a href="http://www.codeandsupply.co/about">goals of Pittsburgh Code and Supply</a>. I&rsquo;m very excited about this new group!</p>

<p>The Code and Supply meetup I just attended was about <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/186766512/">&ldquo;Programming in journalism&rdquo;</a>. This is a topic of huge importance, and I was excited to attend to hear more about what some local journalist/programmers are doing.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>A bit about sponsors</h2>

<p>Justin opened by briefly saying a few words about the goals of Pittsburgh Code and Supply. He then noted that this month, the group did not have sponsors, unfortunately.</p>

<p><strong>Pittsburgh Code and Supply needs sponsors!</strong></p>

<p>If you like what Code and Supply is doing, please consider seeing if your employer would be willing to step up as a sponsor for the group.</p>

<h2>Contribute!</h2>

<p>Also, in any case, spread the word about the group.</p>

<p>This is my first meeting, and next Monday, I am actually going to give my first presentation for the group, on <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/183483622/">&ldquo;Type-Directed TDD in Rust&rdquo;</a>. The group is always looking for people to speak about something or facilitate other formats of meetings, so <a href="http://www.codeandsupply.co/speak/">sign up</a> if you have an idea! I personally have some ideas I&rsquo;d like to propose for future meetings, such as discussions about technology-related topics such as philosophy, history, and education.</p>

<h2>AmyJo Brown</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/DaOxhNkHvvw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p><a href="http://amyjobrown.com/">AmyJo Brown</a>, an independent journalist, gave a great talk about the kind of work that she does, and why it is important. She gave an overview of how journalism has changed because of the availability of data and because of the complexity of the world, both of which lead to the necessity of telling stories differently, as evidenced by what <a href="http://www.propublica.org/">ProPublica</a>, the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/">New York Times</a>, and the <a href="http://www.latimes.com/">Los Angeles Times</a> have been doing.</p>

<p>Her own work involves tracking political donations (&ldquo;follow the money&rdquo;).</p>

<p>She gave examples of software tools she uses to get data, clean it, analyze it, and archive the whole process. On the programming end, she programs in Python, for example (Django for Web development), and uses <a href="http://www.documentcloud.org/">DocumentCloud</a>.</p>

<p>She talked about many things to keep in mind while doing this kind of data journalism. First of all, you have to know the limitations of the data you&rsquo;re getting. She has to deal with handwritten documents, and data in different formats. Data that is clearly incomplete or entered wrong (whether accidentally or maliciously). It is necessary to know the domain, know the context in which data was collected or required or submitted, to not fall into the trap of just blindly treating data as a record of the full truth and just get into programmatically processing it. There&rsquo;s a lot that involves human judgment calls. And this is why it is so important to save all the original information and document each step of data &ldquo;cleaning&rdquo; and interpretation.</p>

<p>Near the end of her talk, AmyJo had her colleague Katrina speak a bit also. Katrina was not originally trained as a programmer, but was always interested in politics. She ended up getting into programming later.</p>

<p>(I&rsquo;m always very excited and impressed to hear of people with domain knowledge and passion who take up computer programming as a useful skill to apply to their domain. Sometimes I hear people saying &ldquo;please don&rsquo;t code&rdquo;; I totally disagree with this sentiment and believe that <a href="http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/09/why-everyone-should-learn-computer-science/">everyone can benefit from learning the fundamentals of computer science and programming</a>.)</p>

<h2>Andrew McGill</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/0iT9rhwRXVs" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p><a href="http://www.andrewrmcgill.com/">Andrew McGill</a> bills himself as &ldquo;your friendly neighborhood journalist&rdquo;, and works for the <a href="http://www.post-gazette.com/">Pittsburgh Post-Gazette</a>.</p>

<p>He started by talking about his interesting career path, which involved being into computers before college, but then going to college and then finding other interests and abandoning programming, and then only later taking it back up, in the service of journalism, to enable him to find data and tell stories through visualization.</p>

<p>He showed us specific Web sites and articles he has created to provide better visualizations of data than what is available in raw form. For example, on the funny side, there is <a href="http://newsinteractive.post-gazette.com/wheresbill/">&ldquo;Where&rsquo;s Bill?&rdquo;</a>, which he created because he was not happy with the &ldquo;official&rdquo; boring text news feed of Mayor Bill Peduto&rsquo;s calendar. He scraped the official site with PHP. He also created a Bill Peduto Twitter bot using Python.</p>

<p>He also showed a D3-based visualization of <a href="http://newsinteractive.post-gazette.com/plugged-wells/">&ldquo;The Mystery of the Plugged Wells&rdquo;</a>. Again, the point was to take already available data but to tell a story better with it than just giving raw tables or a purely text-based narrative.</p>

<p>He showed some other projects, such as a visualization of school comparisons based on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pennsylvania_System_of_School_Assessment">PSSA</a> data.</p>

<h2>Questions and answers</h2>

<p>There were quite a lot of questions posed to the presenters throughout the evening, on the technologies used, on work with graphic designers, on the process of obtaining data, and political implications of the work. Great discussions.</p>

<h2>Technologies used</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s something resembling a summary of technologies mentioned that the presenters use:</p>

<ul>
<li>Python</li>
<li>Django</li>
<li>DocumentCloud</li>
<li>Bootstrap</li>
<li>Git</li>
<li>R</li>
<li>SQL</li>
<li>OpenRefine</li>
<li>D3</li>
</ul>


<h2>Interesting articles</h2>

<p>Before the meetup, I posted to the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/186766512/">event page</a> a link to a provocative (perhaps too harsh and ranty) article warning about dangers in data journalism, <a href="http://www.niemanlab.org/2014/07/alberto-cairo-data-journalism-needs-to-up-its-own-standards/">by visualization expert Alberto Cairo</a>. It got no response.</p>

<p>Later, I also posted a link to a thoughtful examination of the question of <a href="http://source.opennews.org/en-US/learning/true-facts-maybe/">epistemology in data journalism</a>. I totally recommend reading that article.</p>

<p>AmyJo after the meetup posted some more links on the event page:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@jeremybowers/why-im-a-newsroom-coder-860d9d49f684">&ldquo;Why I&rsquo;m a newsroom coder&rdquo;</a></li>
<li><a href="https://source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/planting-next-crop-newsroom-coders/">&ldquo;Planting the next crop of newsroom coders&rdquo;</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/17/opinion/the-fec-lags-on-campaign-finance-disclosures.html">&ldquo;Data delayed is democracy denied&rdquo;</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I was very excited to attend my first Pittsburgh Code and Supply meetup, on the fascinating topic of programming in journalism. I felt I learned a lot about what is at stake and how programming is being used in journalism to better inform people of what is going on in the world.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pittsburgh Data Visualization: D3 and only D3]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/08/22/pittsburgh-data-visualization-d3-and-only-d3/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-22T22:01:22-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/08/22/pittsburgh-data-visualization-d3-and-only-d3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Patrick gave a presentation for the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Data-Visualization-Group/">Pittsburgh Data Visualization Meetup</a> on <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Data-Visualization-Group/events/135374702/">only D3</a>, because there was interest after the <a href="/blog/2013/08/07/pittsburgh-data-visualization-d3-and-r/">previous meetup</a> for more on D3.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Patrick started with a review of last time, on selections, data, callbacks, and transitions.</p>

<p>Then he went into the use of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heat_map">heat maps</a>.</p>

<p>Finally, he went into forces.</p>

<p>I have to confess that I got lost in the presentation because of the volume of code presented and my unfamiliarity with the API. I believe that I&rsquo;ve reached the limit of what I can passively absorb about using D3, and simply need to get down and dirty and create my own project.</p>

<p>I was also feeling really tired and on the verge of getting sick. I felt very cold in the room and did not have a jacket on me in the summer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pittsburgh Data Visualization: D3 and R]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/08/07/pittsburgh-data-visualization-d3-and-r/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-07T22:19:55-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/08/07/pittsburgh-data-visualization-d3-and-r</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a week ago, the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Data-Visualization-Group/">Pittsburgh Data Visualization Meetup</a> launched with a <a href="/blog/2013/07/30/pittsburgh-data-visualization-meetup-inaugural-meet-and-greet/">&ldquo;meet and greet&rdquo; that I attended</a>. Today was <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Data-Visualization-Group/events/132375562/">our first actual presentation-based meeting</a>, with speakers giving introductions to both D3 and R.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Location</h2>

<p>The meeting was on the Pitt campus. Unfortunately, this meant no WiFi access, because guest WiFi requires a sponsor and is a hassle to set up. So this is not the perfect place to meet, but was available to Patrick in the summer.</p>

<p>About 15 people showed up.</p>

<h2>Patrick on D3</h2>

<p>By popular demand, Patrick gave an introduction to D3.</p>

<p>He is particularly interested in knowledge discovery in data mining. He gave an example of converting data from HTML to XML to SVG and then finally getting it into D3.</p>

<p>Although D3 is a JavaScript library, its API feels like its own domain-specific language with its own conventions, so there&rsquo;s a learning curve. Patrick gave a demo of hooking data up to D3 and then changing the data, and hooking up mouse events. He showed transitions for visualization when data changes. Apparently D3 does an efficient recalculation of what needs to happen when data changes.</p>

<p>He also showed a force-directed graph.</p>

<h2>Rihanna on R</h2>

<p>Rihanna spoke about her use of R for her work.</p>

<p>She has been using R for 13 years! She gave an overview of her work flow, which involves using a workspace and saving objects. She likes to get data from raw sources into R and use plots to look for patterns, spikes. Then she makes different plots in order to tell a story.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I found it very informative to hear about the work flows Patrick and Rihanna each adopted in order to find and report on interesting data.</p>

<p>The main drawback of this meeting was that it was very long, because of two talks crammed into one evening. Since this was just the first meeting, I suggested that shorter talks in the future would enable more time for unstructured discussion at meetings.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pittsburgh Data Visualization Meetup: inaugural meet and greet]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/07/30/pittsburgh-data-visualization-meetup-inaugural-meet-and-greet/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-30T23:42:33-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/07/30/pittsburgh-data-visualization-meetup-inaugural-meet-and-greet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is a new <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Data-Visualization-Group/">Pittsburgh Data Visualization Meetup</a> and I attended the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Data-Visualization-Group/events/128665542/">first meeting</a>, which was a meet and greet at <a href="http://www.fuelandfuddle.com/">Fuel &amp; Fuddle</a> in Oakland.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>My interest in data visualization</h2>

<p>Data visualization isn&rsquo;t something I&rsquo;ve done much of, but is something I&rsquo;m interested in, both for work and for my own personal project ideas. For example, I have amassed a lot of personal data about the races I&rsquo;ve run and the chess games I&rsquo;ve played.</p>

<p>The only thing I&rsquo;ve done for visualization at work is generate static images using <a href="http://www.graphviz.org/">Graphviz</a> to display, in human-friendly form, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grammatical_relation">grammatical relations</a> that are otherwise represented using a text format; this text format is usually automatically generated, but sometimes has errors that humans have to fix. It is hard to either see or fix such errors from the text representation, so the visual display helps a lot. Unfortunately, right now our program only generates a static image, not an interactive and editable representation of each graph, so the user who sees something wrong has to edit the text and regenerate the image to verify the correction visually. Ideally we would like to make the program more interactive, but this task is not performed very often, so I had gone with the simplest possible solution.</p>

<h2>Summary of meeting</h2>

<p>This being the first meeting, we all introduced ourselves and chatted over dinner. The creator of the new meetup is Patrick Dudas, who is involved in all kinds of cool projects in collecting data (such as scraping Twitter) and visualizing it.</p>

<p>People talked about the kind of work they do and the tools they use or would like to switch to using. There was a good variety of people from different disciplines, from science to business, all with a need to create useful visualizations to analyze and report on data.</p>

<p>Libraries and languages mentioned included D3, ggplot, R, Python, and Tableau. There was particular interest in more effective use of D3 and R. Patrick promised to lead a session on D3 soon.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>It was good to see a new meetup revolving around a need and a discipline, visualization, that cuts across different disciplines and programming languages.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
