<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: showclix | The Conscientious Programmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/categories/showclix/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-18T01:08:23-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Franklin Chen]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[franklinchen@franklinchen.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pittsburgh Node Meetup: Optimizing development workflow with Grunt]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/07/31/pittsburgh-node-meetup-optimizing-development-workflow-with-grunt/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-31T21:29:45-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/07/31/pittsburgh-node-meetup-optimizing-development-workflow-with-grunt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am not a <a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node</a> developer. I&rsquo;ve only used Node to play around with JavaScript, not for any real work or personal projects (yet). The last time I used Node was two months ago, for a <a href="http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/06/01/pittsburgh-tech-fest-2013-my-talk-stop-overusing-regular-expressions/">talk I gave at Pittsburgh TechFest 2013</a> in which I wrote JavaScript code running on Node, but did not actually talk about it, and only mentioned that I had written it and put it up on my <a href="https://github.com/franklinchen/talk-on-overusing-regular-expressions">GitHub repository for the talk</a>.</p>

<p>That is why it took me so long to attend my first <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Node-js/">Pittsburgh Node</a> <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Node-js/events/128439692/">meeting</a>. I was simply curious who was involved in the local Node community and what tooling they were using. The meeting was about <a href="http://gruntjs.com/">Grunt</a>, a Make-like task runner. Nate Good of ShowClix presented.</p>

<h2>Attendance</h2>

<p>There was a fairly large group of people who attended: around thirty. Node seems to be popular in town.</p>

<h2>The talk</h2>

<p>Overall, Grunt seemed like Make or Rake. You can use plugins and define your own tasks. So there seemed nothing special about it, other than it is a useful tool corresponding to similar tools for other language ecosystems.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Since I don&rsquo;t really use Node, I went to the meetup out of curiosity more than anything else. I will probably not attend again. There seemed a lot of enthusiasm though.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
