<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Node on The Conscientious Programmer</title>
    <link>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/categories/node/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Node on The Conscientious Programmer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2013 22:03:55 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/categories/node/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>MongoDB free online course: a review</title>
      <link>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2013/12/04/mongodb-free-online-course-a-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2013 22:03:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2013/12/04/mongodb-free-online-course-a-review/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mongodb.com/sites/all/themes/bonsai/logo.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;MongoDB logo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally finished a two-month &lt;a href=&#34;http://education.mongodb.com/&#34;&gt;free online course on MongoDB&lt;/a&gt;, given by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mongodb.com/&#34;&gt;MongoDB, Inc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a review of the specific course numbered M101J, &amp;ldquo;MongoDB for Java Developers&amp;rdquo;, but it should apply to all thee introductory developer courses on MongoDB in any language, because actually, I had originally signed up months earlier for their original course (in JavaScript), and the content is largely the same (I had gotten busy and dropped that course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-learn-mongodb:0d4164e2dd5b7ba3716ef93bdba00ac4&#34;&gt;Why learn MongoDB?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had first heard of MongoDB over two years ago, at a meeting of the (now defunct) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-JavaScript-Developers/&#34;&gt;original Pittsburgh JavaScript meetup group&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-JavaScript-Developers/events/25229441/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;In-depth look at Node.js and NoSQL&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MongoDB has become very popular; as far as I can tell, this is because of extreme marketing efforts, as well as the fact that it is very easy to get started doing stuff with it, being a document-oriented NoSQL database requiring no schema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took this course in part to expose myself to some NoSQL technology and also in part because I anticipated needing to use something like it. In fact, it turns out &lt;a href=&#34;http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/08/02/pittsburgh-ruby-python-social/&#34;&gt;I did use it&lt;/a&gt;, heavily, in exactly the kind of use case that works fine with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-did-i-take-the-java-version-of-the-course:0d4164e2dd5b7ba3716ef93bdba00ac4&#34;&gt;Why did I take the Java version of the course?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the &amp;ldquo;M101J: MongoDB for Java Developers&amp;rdquo; version of the course because I anticipated writing code in Scala to access MongoDB. In fact, during the course, I ended up using the official Scala driver &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mongodb/casbah&#34;&gt;Casbah&lt;/a&gt; when possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary-of-the-course:0d4164e2dd5b7ba3716ef93bdba00ac4&#34;&gt;Summary of the course&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the course actually involved using the JavaScript-based MongoDB shell, which makes sense because it is easy to explore data that way. Since everything is JSON-like, there&amp;rsquo;s no real escaping JavaScript if you&amp;rsquo;re working with MongoDB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video lecture/quiz/assignment format is fairly standard for MOOCs, and worked fairly well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course was more work than I expected, because it lasted so long, two months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ad hoc nature of MongoDB&amp;rsquo;s API (including the Java-based one) tended to bother me throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weird CRUD syntax, shoehorning everything into a JSON representation, took some getting used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way to specify indexes and to evaluate your guesses about whether they are actually working the way you expected was to look at funny values in JSON. I found this low-level and annoying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aggregation API seemed even weirder. Overall, everything had a loose &amp;ldquo;dynamic&amp;rdquo; feel to it: this is the essence of MongoDB, really. Doing things wrong made me frustrated because of the runtime errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the sections on replication and sharding were particularly problematic. The lectures kept mentioning that various defaults and APIs were a moving target. Furthermore, actual hardcoded numbers even showed up that we were supposed to use to specify policies. Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:0d4164e2dd5b7ba3716ef93bdba00ac4&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lectures and quizzes were well-designed (until the final portion of the course that seemed particularly ad hoc). The assignments were sometimes rather tricky, with not much of a hint, but offered a decent variety of realistic query formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would recommend this course as an overview to anyone who is committed to using MongoDB to its full extent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although I got my &amp;ldquo;certificate&amp;rdquo; for completing the course, and appreciate that MongoDB, Inc offers this training for free, I felt that there was a lot of ad hoc stuff going on in the evolving design of MongoDB, and embedded in the API design as well. For what I needed to know for my work, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really need the whole course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Node Meetup: Optimizing development workflow with Grunt</title>
      <link>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2013/07/31/pittsburgh-node-meetup-optimizing-development-workflow-with-grunt/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2013 21:29:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2013/07/31/pittsburgh-node-meetup-optimizing-development-workflow-with-grunt/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I am not a &lt;a href=&#34;http://nodejs.org/&#34;&gt;Node&lt;/a&gt; developer. I&amp;rsquo;ve only used Node to play around with JavaScript, not for any real work or personal projects (yet). The last time I used Node was two months ago, for a &lt;a href=&#34;http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/06/01/pittsburgh-tech-fest-2013-my-talk-stop-overusing-regular-expressions/&#34;&gt;talk I gave at Pittsburgh TechFest 2013&lt;/a&gt; in which I wrote JavaScript code running on Node, but did not actually talk about it, and only mentioned that I had written it and put it up on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/franklinchen/talk-on-overusing-regular-expressions&#34;&gt;GitHub repository for the talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why it took me so long to attend my first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Node-js/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Node&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Node-js/events/128439692/&#34;&gt;meeting&lt;/a&gt;. I was simply curious who was involved in the local Node community and what tooling they were using. The meeting was about &lt;a href=&#34;http://gruntjs.com/&#34;&gt;Grunt&lt;/a&gt;, a Make-like task runner. Nate Good of ShowClix presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;attendance:89eab02fcac62478e1d2cec2100846be&#34;&gt;Attendance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a fairly large group of people who attended: around thirty. Node seems to be popular in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-talk:89eab02fcac62478e1d2cec2100846be&#34;&gt;The talk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, Grunt seemed like Make or Rake. You can use plugins and define your own tasks. So there seemed nothing special about it, other than it is a useful tool corresponding to similar tools for other language ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:89eab02fcac62478e1d2cec2100846be&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I don&amp;rsquo;t really use Node, I went to the meetup out of curiosity more than anything else. I will probably not attend again. There seemed a lot of enthusiasm though.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>