<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Futures on The Conscientious Programmer</title>
    <link>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/categories/futures/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Futures on The Conscientious Programmer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 21:29:20 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/categories/futures/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Scala Meetup: Introduction to Reactive</title>
      <link>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2014/01/09/pittsburgh-scala-meetup-introduction-to-reactive/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 21:29:20 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2014/01/09/pittsburgh-scala-meetup-introduction-to-reactive/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Scala-Meetup/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Scala Meetup&lt;/a&gt; met with Josh presenting an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Scala-Meetup/events/146581352/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Introduction to Reactive&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pre-meetup-dinner:1fbca7bab37ee55bb74190d8ff39e5b7&#34;&gt;Pre-meetup dinner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of us (Justin, Josh, Chris, me) had an early dinner at Everyday Noodles before the meetup. Very filling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;turnout:1fbca7bab37ee55bb74190d8ff39e5b7&#34;&gt;Turnout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten of us showed up for this meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;presentation:1fbca7bab37ee55bb74190d8ff39e5b7&#34;&gt;Presentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-reactive-anyway:1fbca7bab37ee55bb74190d8ff39e5b7&#34;&gt;What is &amp;ldquo;reactive&amp;rdquo; anyway?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you didn&amp;rsquo;t hear about it in the media, the term &amp;ldquo;reactive&amp;rdquo; has been popularized in recent months, and I &lt;a href=&#34;http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/31/review-of-the-free-coursera-course-principles-of-reactive-programming/&#34;&gt;reviewed the free Coursera course &amp;ldquo;Principles of Reactive Programming&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; that some of us in the Pittsburgh Scala group just completed, so check out my post for more on &amp;ldquo;reactive&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;futures:1fbca7bab37ee55bb74190d8ff39e5b7&#34;&gt;Futures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Josh did a live SBT session reviewing futures and promises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He noted that futures have limitations as a component of reactive systems. (This had become apparent when &lt;a href=&#34;http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/25/openhack-pittsburgh-exploring-scala-odds-and-ends/&#34;&gt;I started using futures last year in my personal projects&lt;/a&gt; and then &lt;a href=&#34;http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/08/02/pittsburgh-ruby-python-social/&#34;&gt;for work&lt;/a&gt;.) By themselves, futures do not support cancellation or &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Back_pressure&#34;&gt;back pressure&lt;/a&gt;. Futures are a low-level, limited mechanism that are the right tool only if you have a pipeline all the way through forward, no back channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative to futures, of course, is to go all out and use Akka actors. But the drawback I&amp;rsquo;ve found with that is that this is a heavyweight mechanism for problems that don&amp;rsquo;t need the full power of actors. I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted something more structured and lightweight than using actors directly. I find it tricky to program using actors, because it is very easy to start writing spaghetti code that is spread out everywhere (which is what happened to me in the final project for the Coursera course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out, according to Josh, that Typesafe is working on precisely this problem! Nice. He&amp;rsquo;ll tell us more when it comes out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-10:1fbca7bab37ee55bb74190d8ff39e5b7&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-10)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half a year later, the promise was realized, as the Pittsburgh Scala Meetup had Josh &lt;a href=&#34;http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2014/07/10/pittsburgh-scala-meetup-reactive-streams/&#34;&gt;gave a talk on the new API called Reactive Streams&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;play:1fbca7bab37ee55bb74190d8ff39e5b7&#34;&gt;Play&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Josh demonstrated &lt;a href=&#34;http://typesafe.com/activator&#34;&gt;Typesafe Activator&lt;/a&gt;, the cool new Web browser-based platform for using Scala. He showed an app using Play that looks at blogs simultaneously and uses &lt;code&gt;recoverWith&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;random-other-questions-and-discussions:1fbca7bab37ee55bb74190d8ff39e5b7&#34;&gt;Random other questions and discussions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I like about the Pittsburgh Scala Meetup is that even when we have a presentation, discussion often wanders off to related topics (or unrelated topics). Anything goes, and I usually learn a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone asked about support for channels as in Go or Clojure&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/clojure/core.async&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;core.async&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Josh said they&amp;rsquo;re working on this sort of thing with support for back pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone asked about how to connect &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.playframework.com/documentation/2.0/Iteratees&#34;&gt;iteratees&lt;/a&gt; with actors. Josh said, you can feed from an iteratee to an actor, and then just let the actor do stuff. However, there is some controversy about the whole iteratee thing in Play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:1fbca7bab37ee55bb74190d8ff39e5b7&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a great Pittsburgh Scala Meetup session. I felt that a lot of questions that had built up in my mind after having gotten into reactive programming are being addressed with continuing work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Ruby/Python social and some observations about our polyglot world</title>
      <link>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2013/08/02/pittsburgh-ruby-python-social</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2013 22:17:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2013/08/02/pittsburgh-ruby-python-social</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Programming meetups aren&amp;rsquo;t just about presentations and coding. Abby and I joined others in meeting up for dinner for a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburgh-ruby/events/120201652/&#34;&gt;joint Pittsburgh Ruby and Pittsburgh Python social&lt;/a&gt; and enjoyed relaxing and socializing outdoors in Bakery Square. Although it perpetually looked like it was going to rain, it turned out we weren&amp;rsquo;t really rained on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;//instagram.com/p/ch8quus4Kb/embed/&#34; width=&#34;612&#34; height=&#34;710&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carol, Andre, and Abby:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/carolnichols/9425969330&#34; title=&#34;ttm! by Carol Nichols, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3754/9425969330_d8ecdbf987.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; alt=&#34;ttm!&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fitting that there was a joint social for two language communities, because we live in a polyglot world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite my original intention not to engage into any tech-related conversation, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help remarking on my current polyglot responsibilities at work at CMU on the METAL project!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-polyglot-world-ruby-python-perl:f96e1a748b79a0448958de0b51234d51&#34;&gt;Our polyglot world: Ruby, Python, Perl&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned having to cobble together Ruby, Python, and Perl code recently in an NLP project to process Farsi text into corpora to analyze. We used a Ruby gem &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/aziz/virastar&#34;&gt;Virastar&lt;/a&gt; in our pipeline, a Perl script for a Farsi stemmer, &lt;a href=&#34;http://perstem.sourceforge.net/&#34;&gt;Perstem&lt;/a&gt;, and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wfeely/farsiNLPTools&#34;&gt;Python script for normalization&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-12-04-c-scala-mongodb:f96e1a748b79a0448958de0b51234d51&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-12-04) C++, Scala, MongoDB&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work project ended up becoming even more polyglot than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also used a C++ tagger, TurboTagger from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ark.cs.cmu.edu/TurboParser/&#34;&gt;TurboParser&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote Scala to execute and monitor the pipeline, because it turned out that component bugs and timeouts (from infinite loops sometimes) had to be dealt with: the original shell script pipelines did not handle any of that at all. Also, the vast amount of data meant that parallelizing was critical. The Scala ecosystem has  turned out great for me. I didn&amp;rsquo;t use Akka actors for this task, just futures and parallel collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also used MongoDB because it is quite a natural fit for document-oriented storage and querying as an intermediate stage I can inspect before the final stage of conversion to Sketch Engine format. And I happened to just &lt;a href=&#34;http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/04/mongodb-free-online-course-a-review/&#34;&gt;finish a free online MongoDB course&lt;/a&gt; which has been useful. In my Scala code, I used the official Scala driver &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mongodb/casbah&#34;&gt;Casbah&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why MongoDB? I needed to track the transformations, and experiment with different parameters while also fixing bugs and rerunning stuff. Because there is so much data and sometimes something crashes in the pipeline, I decided to save all intermediate results in a database in order to avoid repeating work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I used Scala to generate corpora for importing into &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sketchengine.co.uk/&#34;&gt;The Sketch Engine&lt;/a&gt; for our Farsi linguistics experts to analyze. Scala&amp;rsquo;s parser combinator library came in very useful, and I represented each stage in the pipeline as a transformation of a custom AST designed to finally serialize well to the Sketch Engine &amp;ldquo;vert&amp;rdquo; file format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was pretty important to work with ASTs, since we actually got text in a variety of formats, which I parsed to a common AST in order to push into the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whew!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-06-10:f96e1a748b79a0448958de0b51234d51&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-06-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A description of some of this &lt;a href=&#34;http://springfield.metaphor.cs.cmu.edu:8080/MetaphorViz/About.html&#34;&gt;METAL project&lt;/a&gt; work is in the paper &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2014/pdf/596_Paper.pdf&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The CMU METAL Farsi NLP Approach&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>