<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Parallelism on The Conscientious Programmer</title>
    <link>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/categories/parallelism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Parallelism on The Conscientious Programmer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 May 2014 22:49:48 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/categories/parallelism/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Scala Meetup: Exploring type-directed, test-driven development using FizzBuzz (my practice talk)</title>
      <link>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2014/05/15/pittsburgh-scala-meetup-exploring-type-directed/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2014 22:49:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2014/05/15/pittsburgh-scala-meetup-exploring-type-directed/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Scala-Meetup/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Scala Meetup&lt;/a&gt; met, with me presenting a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Scala-Meetup/events/146581402/&#34;&gt;practice talk&lt;/a&gt; for &amp;ldquo;Exploring type-directed, test-driven development using FizzBuzz&amp;rdquo;, which I am presenting at the upcoming local &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghtechfest.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh TechFest&lt;/a&gt; conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;presentation:0ca97438327f3bcfe743d5a186e4af3e&#34;&gt;Presentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only recently completed the slides and code for my talk, and had not actually given the talk yet, so this was a practice talk that did not go so well, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spoke too quickly and had too much material to cover, and also got lost in some of my own slides. Oops. I think reaction to my talk was mixed. Some enjoyed it, while others seemed lost at places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After going home, I frankly felt that I had &lt;em&gt;failed&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I believe I can do much better. I have plenty of time to do a thorough revision before Pittsburgh TechFest in three weeks. I need to cut out material that is not needed for the core of what I am trying to achieve and make some things clearer (especially for the intended Pittsburgh TechFest audience, which I do not expect to even know Scala).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;supporting-material:0ca97438327f3bcfe743d5a186e4af3e&#34;&gt;Supporting material&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/FranklinChen/talk-on-type-directed-tdd-using-fizzbuzz&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t recommend looking at them, but for historical purposes, here are slides of the presentation &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/FranklinChen/talk-on-type-directed-tdd-using-fizzbuzz/blob/meetup/doc/presentation.pdf&#34;&gt;as it was given in the first draft&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-05-16:0ca97438327f3bcfe743d5a186e4af3e&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-05-16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day makes a difference in my confidence and determination! I noticed that the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Code and Supply&lt;/a&gt; group (which I have not yet attended) is soon having its inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rust-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/181773312/&#34;&gt;soon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided to offer to do a version of my talk for Pittsburgh Code and Supply using Rust as the programming language (rather than Scala). I want to spread the news about how to effectively use a sufficiently typed programming language, whether it&amp;rsquo;s Scala or Rust or anything else sufficiently derived from the ML family of type systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Justin will schedule it for some time in July. That should give me enough time, after Pittsburgh TechFest in early June, to learn enough Rust to convert my Scala code over properly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-06-07:0ca97438327f3bcfe743d5a186e4af3e&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-06-07)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I much improved the presentation for Pittsburgh TechFest, which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/06/07/report-on-the-2014-pittsburgh-techfest-my-third-year/&#34;&gt;attended for the third year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend reading the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/FranklinChen/talk-on-type-directed-tdd-using-fizzbuzz/blob/master/doc/article.pdf&#34;&gt;article version of the presentation&lt;/a&gt;, rather than the slides. This is the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve created both an article version of a presentation and slides for use during the live presentation. I will do this in the future as well. Slides are not meant to stand alone or even be read alone, but in case you really want to see them, they are here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/37257104&#34; width=&#34;427&#34; height=&#34;356&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; style=&#34;border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom:5px&#34;&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/FranklinChen/presentation-37257104&#34; title=&#34;Exploring type-directed, test-driven development: a case study using FizzBuzz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Exploring type-directed, test-driven development: a case study using FizzBuzz&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/FranklinChen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Franklin Chen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-17:0ca97438327f3bcfe743d5a186e4af3e&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s crunch time. My Rust version of the talk, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/183483622/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Type-Directed TDD in Rust&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; is coming next week.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Ruby/Python social and some observations about our polyglot world</title>
      <link>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2013/08/02/pittsburgh-ruby-python-social/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2013 22:17:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2013/08/02/pittsburgh-ruby-python-social/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Programming meetups aren&amp;rsquo;t just about presentations and coding. Abby and I joined others in meeting up for dinner for a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburgh-ruby/events/120201652/&#34;&gt;joint Pittsburgh Ruby and Pittsburgh Python social&lt;/a&gt; and enjoyed relaxing and socializing outdoors in Bakery Square. Although it perpetually looked like it was going to rain, it turned out we weren&amp;rsquo;t really rained on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;//instagram.com/p/ch8quus4Kb/embed/&#34; width=&#34;612&#34; height=&#34;710&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carol, Andre, and Abby:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/carolnichols/9425969330&#34; title=&#34;ttm! by Carol Nichols, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3754/9425969330_d8ecdbf987.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; alt=&#34;ttm!&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fitting that there was a joint social for two language communities, because we live in a polyglot world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite my original intention not to engage into any tech-related conversation, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help remarking on my current polyglot responsibilities at work at CMU on the METAL project!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-polyglot-world-ruby-python-perl:f96e1a748b79a0448958de0b51234d51&#34;&gt;Our polyglot world: Ruby, Python, Perl&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned having to cobble together Ruby, Python, and Perl code recently in an NLP project to process Farsi text into corpora to analyze. We used a Ruby gem &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/aziz/virastar&#34;&gt;Virastar&lt;/a&gt; in our pipeline, a Perl script for a Farsi stemmer, &lt;a href=&#34;http://perstem.sourceforge.net/&#34;&gt;Perstem&lt;/a&gt;, and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wfeely/farsiNLPTools&#34;&gt;Python script for normalization&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-12-04-c-scala-mongodb:f96e1a748b79a0448958de0b51234d51&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-12-04) C++, Scala, MongoDB&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work project ended up becoming even more polyglot than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also used a C++ tagger, TurboTagger from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ark.cs.cmu.edu/TurboParser/&#34;&gt;TurboParser&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote Scala to execute and monitor the pipeline, because it turned out that component bugs and timeouts (from infinite loops sometimes) had to be dealt with: the original shell script pipelines did not handle any of that at all. Also, the vast amount of data meant that parallelizing was critical. The Scala ecosystem has  turned out great for me. I didn&amp;rsquo;t use Akka actors for this task, just futures and parallel collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also used MongoDB because it is quite a natural fit for document-oriented storage and querying as an intermediate stage I can inspect before the final stage of conversion to Sketch Engine format. And I happened to just &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/12/04/mongodb-free-online-course-a-review/&#34;&gt;finish a free online MongoDB course&lt;/a&gt; which has been useful. In my Scala code, I used the official Scala driver &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mongodb/casbah&#34;&gt;Casbah&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why MongoDB? I needed to track the transformations, and experiment with different parameters while also fixing bugs and rerunning stuff. Because there is so much data and sometimes something crashes in the pipeline, I decided to save all intermediate results in a database in order to avoid repeating work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I used Scala to generate corpora for importing into &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sketchengine.co.uk/&#34;&gt;The Sketch Engine&lt;/a&gt; for our Farsi linguistics experts to analyze. Scala&amp;rsquo;s parser combinator library came in very useful, and I represented each stage in the pipeline as a transformation of a custom AST designed to finally serialize well to the Sketch Engine &amp;ldquo;vert&amp;rdquo; file format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was pretty important to work with ASTs, since we actually got text in a variety of formats, which I parsed to a common AST in order to push into the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whew!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-06-10:f96e1a748b79a0448958de0b51234d51&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-06-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A description of some of this &lt;a href=&#34;http://springfield.metaphor.cs.cmu.edu:8080/MetaphorViz/About.html&#34;&gt;METAL project&lt;/a&gt; work is in the paper &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2014/pdf/596_Paper.pdf&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The CMU METAL Farsi NLP Approach&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh JavaScript meetup: functional programming</title>
      <link>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2013/07/10/pittsburgh-javascript-meetup-functional-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 22:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2013/07/10/pittsburgh-javascript-meetup-functional-programming/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://photos3.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/7/f/6/e/global_239372622.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh JavaScript&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because the topic of the featured presentation by &lt;a href=&#34;http://idiotcoder.com/&#34;&gt;Richard Ashkettle&lt;/a&gt; was &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Functional_programming&#34;&gt;functional programming&lt;/a&gt;, I made sure to attend my first meeting of the newly revived &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-JavaScript/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh JavaScript meetup&lt;/a&gt;. (This was actually the third meeting of the revived Pittsburgh JavaScript group, but I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been able to make it to the first two.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d met Richard earlier, a month ago at &lt;a href=&#34;http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/06/01/report-on-the-second-pittsburgh-techfest-2013/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh TechFest&lt;/a&gt;. He does not claim to be an expert at functional programming, but is enthusiastic about concepts and techniques that he can and does apply to improving software quality in many dimensions. Since I have been a functional programming enthusiast and practitioner for twenty years, I had these goals in attending his presentations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;evaluate what Richard and others have done with, and think is important about,  functional programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;offer a few corrections, elaborations, suggestions as appropriate for the situation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gather information on how I may be able to effectively explain functional programming to those who are new to it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;history-of-the-pittsbugh-javascript-meetup-group:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;History of the Pittsbugh JavaScript meetup group&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, in 2011, I had attended the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-JavaScript-Developers&#34;&gt;first incarnation of the group&lt;/a&gt; faithfully, attending several months of meetings before it disbanded when the founder left Pittsburgh. I learned quite a bit from those meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years is a long time in the world of JavaScript. Looking back at &lt;a href=&#34;http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/27/when-jquery-attacks/&#34;&gt;one of my blog posts reporting on the old JavaScript meetup group&lt;/a&gt;, I am amused by how anachronistic that feels to me today, as in my mention of &lt;a href=&#34;http://sproutcore.com/&#34;&gt;Sproutcore&lt;/a&gt;, which I never hear about any more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;up-front-my-take-on-the-secret-of-javascript:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Up front: my take on the secret of JavaScript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some observations (not novel) I have about JavaScript, to set the stage for further discussion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JavaScript is full of horrible, disgusting Bad Parts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JavaScript has only one shiny Good Part: it has first-class functions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People manage to get a lot of amazingly cool and important stuff done using JavaScript, so take it seriously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;comments-on-richard-s-presentation:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Comments on Richard&amp;rsquo;s presentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;immutability-and-functional-languages:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Immutability and &amp;ldquo;functional languages&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard talked about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immutable_object&#34;&gt;immutability&lt;/a&gt; as being part of what &amp;ldquo;functional programming&amp;rdquo; is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is, and in addition, common best practices in many programming languages these days argue for favoring immutability. I want to emphasize that you don&amp;rsquo;t have to go full-blown into a specialized &amp;ldquo;functional language&amp;rdquo; in order to take advantage of immutability as desired: for example, this tip has long since been known as at least a &amp;ldquo;design pattern&amp;rdquo; in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/06/25/pittsburgh-java-user-group-building-and-evolving-a-java-api/&#34;&gt;Java world&lt;/a&gt;, in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.harukizaemon.com/blog/2010/03/01/functional-programming-in-object-oriented-languages/&#34;&gt;Ruby world&lt;/a&gt;, and basically everywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard suggested that &amp;ldquo;functional languages&amp;rdquo; don&amp;rsquo;t allow mutation. By my definition, this is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; actually true.  I didn&amp;rsquo;t raise an objection during the talk because I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to sidetrack it, but here I have space to elaborate a little. I would argue (but that would have to be another blog post) that the cleanest, most intuitive and novice-accessible &amp;ldquo;functional languages&amp;rdquo;) are those in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ML_%28programming_language%29&#34;&gt;ML&lt;/a&gt; family originally developed in the 1970s and lives on today&amp;rsquo;s popular, industrial-strength dialects of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_ML&#34;&gt;Standard ML&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://ocaml.org/&#34;&gt;OCaml&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://fsharp.org/&#34;&gt;F#&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;ML fully supports mutation&lt;/em&gt;, through &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Standard_ML_Programming/Types#References&#34;&gt;reference cells&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, because of notions like this, I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking that maybe it would be best if we all stopped using the term &amp;ldquo;functional language&amp;rdquo;, because it has sadly become misleading and ambiguous. In particular, people instantly think &amp;ldquo;Haskell&amp;rdquo; when they use the word &amp;ldquo;functional language&amp;rdquo;, when in fact Haskell is a very unusual, unique language (and ecosystem) among languages that one could call &amp;ldquo;functional&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;expressions-functions-evaluation-and-values:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Expressions, functions, evaluation, and values&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Richard put it, &amp;ldquo;favor expressions evaluating to a value&amp;rdquo;. The focus of functional programming is on &lt;em&gt;returning&lt;/em&gt; a value, from an expression that includes function calls, rather than munging some mutable global state, or modifying state through a reference passed into a function as a parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recursion-vs-looping:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Recursion vs. looping?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard noted that one characteristic of functional programming is the use of recursion instead of looping. He gave examples of writing tail-recursive functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One nitpick (which again, I did not bring up during the talk): recursion and looping (as in through &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; constructs such as &lt;code&gt;while&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt;) are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; actually opposed. I will write a blog post later about why conventional looping is best thought of as a derived construct built on top of recursion, and why it might be best to consider conventional looping to be a historical accident and mistake (but a very useful invention given the historical circumstances).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;efficiency-of-recursion:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Efficiency of recursion?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, people brought up the topic of efficiency. I have learned over the years that for many people, the word &amp;ldquo;recursion&amp;rdquo; seems to immediately trigger the word &amp;ldquo;efficiency&amp;rdquo;. Richard did a great job in mentioning that &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.ecmascript.org/doku.php?id=harmony:proper_tail_calls&#34;&gt;EMCAScript 6 is going to have proper tail calls (also called tail call optimization)&lt;/a&gt;, which will make tail recursion equivalent to ordinary looping in terms of space usage. This is &lt;em&gt;hugely important&lt;/em&gt; news, of course. This mandate shows how serious JavaScript is about embracing functional programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;recursion-for-parallelism:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Recursion for parallelism&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond the issue tail recursion, I felt I had to point out that recursive algorithms can offer actual &lt;em&gt;speedup&lt;/em&gt;. The classic examples, of course, are the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~scandal/nesl/alg-sequence.html#quicksort&#34;&gt;parallel speedups of divide-and-conquer algorithms such as quicksort that use recursion&lt;/a&gt;. If you expressed the algorithms by removing the recursion (with a hand-rolled stack as often taught in courses), you would destroy the inherent parallelism. So in the world of parallelism, you want your code to stay naturally recursive! As &lt;a href=&#34;http://adambom.github.io/parallel.js/&#34;&gt;parallel computing comes to JavaScript&lt;/a&gt;, keep this in mind!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;higher-order-functions-first-class-functions:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Higher-order functions, first-class functions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard: &amp;ldquo;A function is an object&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really as simple as that. Functions can be created, stored, passed around. Functions can return other functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s amazing, but I claim that this is JavaScript&amp;rsquo;s one Good Part, its killer feature that surprisingly many languages don&amp;rsquo;t have. And it&amp;rsquo;s the one feature that is used &lt;em&gt;all the time&lt;/em&gt;, not just in esoteric code. From the very beginning, JavaScript had first-class functions, to support callbacks for client code in Web browsers. and &lt;a href=&#34;http://nodejs.org/&#34;&gt;Node&lt;/a&gt; server-side code is nothing if not a whole bunch of &lt;code&gt;function (...)&lt;/code&gt;. Without closures and first-class functions, JavaScript would have been completely useless. Thank goodness &lt;a href=&#34;http://brendaneich.com/2008/04/popularity/&#34;&gt;Brendan Eich was inspired by the Scheme functional language&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;no-methods:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;No methods!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JavaScript not only provides full-fledged functions, but ironically, its weirdest feature, the prototype-based inheritance instead of class-based inheritance, inadvertently has prevented &amp;ldquo;interference&amp;rdquo; from the conventional class-based object-oriented world, which is mostly based not on functions, but on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Method_%28computer_programming%29&#34;&gt;methods&lt;/a&gt; that interference with functions because they are meant to &lt;em&gt;replace&lt;/em&gt; functions (since according to &amp;ldquo;pure&amp;rdquo; object-oriented thinking, functions are evil and computation should involve method calls on objects). &lt;em&gt;JavaScript does not (really) have methods&lt;/em&gt;; it only simulates them, by storing bona fide closures into fields of (map) objects. For example, if you use &lt;a href=&#34;http://emberjs.com&#34;&gt;Ember&lt;/a&gt;, the following code illustrates how the building blocks of typical JavaScript programming involve creating lots of &lt;code&gt;function&lt;/code&gt;s: &lt;code&gt;valueWillChange&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;valudDidChange&lt;/code&gt; are just functions. They are not special things, &amp;ldquo;methods&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34; style=&#34;background: #f8f8f8&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;line-height: 125%&#34;&gt;App.PersonView &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; Ember.View.extend({
  valueWillChange&lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #008000; font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; (obj, keyName, value) {
    &lt;span style=&#34;color: #008000; font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;.changingFrom &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; value;
  }.observesBefore(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #BA2121&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;content.value&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;),
  valueDidChange&lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #008000; font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;(obj, keyName, value) {
      &lt;span style=&#34;color: #408080; font-style: italic&#34;&gt;// only run if updating a value already in the DOM&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span style=&#34;color: #008000; font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #008000; font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;.get(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #BA2121&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;state&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;===&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #BA2121&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;inDOM&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;) {
          &lt;span style=&#34;color: #008000; font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; color &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; value &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #008000; font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;.changingFrom &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;?&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #BA2121&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;green&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #666666&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #BA2121&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;red&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;;
          &lt;span style=&#34;color: #408080; font-style: italic&#34;&gt;// logic&lt;/span&gt;
      }
  }.observes(&lt;span style=&#34;color: #BA2121&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;content.value&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;)
});
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;examples:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard gave some standard examples of using higher-order functions such as &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;filter&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;foreach&lt;/code&gt; as provided in various popular JavaScript libraries such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://underscorejs.org/&#34;&gt;Underscore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a matter of style, he recommended against long, obscure one-liners that involve chaining. I agree. For readability and testability of pipelines, I have found that it is good to break things up into intermediate steps. (Just &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/06/26/pittsburgh-python-night-of-the-favorite-module/&#34;&gt;recently&lt;/a&gt;, Tim Lesher also recommended against stupidity masking as excessive cleverness in his Python lightning talk about functional programming with &lt;code&gt;itertools&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;monads:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Monads?!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regrettably, Richard brought up the term &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monad_%28functional_programming%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;monads&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m close to thinking that this word should be &lt;a href=&#34;http://fsharpforfunandprofit.com/posts/why-i-wont-be-writing-a-monad-tutorial/&#34;&gt;banned&lt;/a&gt;, because too many confusions about them have ruined the word. I have yet decided what the best alternative phrase might be. Maybe something like &amp;ldquo;computational context&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, Richard admitted he was going to abuse the word, and for the sake of example, he said, he was going to say that &amp;ldquo;jQuery is a monad&amp;rdquo;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to derail his talk, and since he admitted the abuse, I decided there would be a better time to address this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting to me, however, that he gathered that the interesting thing about jQuery, and why he wanted to call it a monad, was the chaining of calls in jQuery. I need to think of a good way to deal with this intuition when I get around to explaining monads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;partial-application-and-currying:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Partial application and currying&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard explained both partial application and currying, then he wondered when one would in practice write a curried function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said (but not very convincingly, I think) that you would write a curried function if you knew you would otherwise have to manually do a bunch of partial application. I have to confess that was a weak answer. I think the practical situation in JavaScript is that full-scale up-front currying is not useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;libraries:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Libraries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard recommended checking out the following libraries, especially Lo-Dash, which he judges to be faster than Underscore:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://underscorejs.org/&#34;&gt;Underscore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lodash.com/&#34;&gt;Lo-Dash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://osteele.com/sources/javascript/functional/&#34;&gt;Functional JavaScript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions-and-answers:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Questions and answers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were many interesting questions raised after the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introducing-functional-programming-into-a-team-environment:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Introducing functional programming into a team environment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone asked Richard a good question about whether it&amp;rsquo;s appropriate to, say, start using Underscore at work and expecting other team members to learn how to use it. Is it fair to expect others to learn a new way of doing things that might seem weird?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My point of view is that there&amp;rsquo;s nothing specific about functional programming when it comes to questions like this. The same question comes up when evaluating a particular programming language or a particular MVC framework or a particular version control system, and the answer involve considering all the different realities of who is comfortable with what, whether it is worth learning something new, what the advantages and disadvantages are, how much the decision will affect delivery of business value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;growing-parameter-list-for-a-function-vs-passing-in-a-big-object:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Growing parameter list for a function vs. passing in a big object&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One concern brought up is that if you&amp;rsquo;re programming in a functional style, you can end up being faced with ever-growing parameter lists for a function to pass in everything that it needs. One solution is to create a big object to stick everything into it that might be needed (for example, a configuration object instead of separate flag parameters). Is this overkill?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, &lt;a href=&#34;http://tonylukasavage.com/&#34;&gt;Tony Lukasavage&lt;/a&gt; emphasized that his concern was in the context of the need to evolve an existing API without breaking customers&amp;rsquo; client code that uses it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first note would be that API design is tricky and checking out &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/06/25/pittsburgh-java-user-group-building-and-evolving-a-java-api/&#34;&gt;some resources on API design&lt;/a&gt; is very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding parameter lists, Richard noted that you might have a design problem if you have a function that needs to know about so many things it depends on. You may want to refactor the function (of course, in the context of evolving a mature API that customers depend on, it may be too late, unfortunately) and the data structures passed in. For example, if you have a number of functions that all take as parameters a &lt;code&gt;firstName&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;lastName&lt;/code&gt;, then maybe you want a single &lt;code&gt;name&lt;/code&gt; parameter instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggested also that if certain flags are not always needed, then instead of a huge configuration object, how about simply having separate but related functions (in a language supporting overloading, you could provide overloaded functions, although the topic of overloading is another large one to discuss later), each of which takes only the flags the client cares about. Of course, as some people pointed out, then you might end up with annoyingly long and specific function names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody said designing an API is easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;do-i-actually-do-functional-programming:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Do I actually do functional programming?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One question I got, since before the meetup, I had indicated having experience with functional programming, was basically, do I actually use it in JavaScript and elsewhere. The answer is, yes. As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned, you don&amp;rsquo;t have use a special language in order to program in this way, although it&amp;rsquo;s much easier and more efficient to use a language that is tailored to support it. Most of the code I&amp;rsquo;ve written in the past fifteen years has attempted to be primarily functional in style, whatever language I&amp;rsquo;m using for work (mostly Java, Perl, Python, and recently Scala). I don&amp;rsquo;t do this out of some kind of ideology, but because it works well in getting stuff done. Before adopting a primarily functional style of programming, I spent years working in traditional imperative and object-oriented styles, and empirically, that was less pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;do-i-do-functional-programming-in-javascript:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Do I do functional programming in JavaScript?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not actually done any JavaScript programming for work since doing some UI prototyping two years ago. I don&amp;rsquo;t know when I&amp;rsquo;ll return to doing front end work, but meanwhile, I am interested in doing some Web browser stuff for personal projects, so I try to keep up to date on developments in the JavaScript world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that has been interesting that I need to check out is the rise of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Functional_reactive_programming&#34;&gt;functional reactive programming (FRP)&lt;/a&gt; libraries for JavaScript, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/raimohanska/bacon.js&#34;&gt;Bacon.js&lt;/a&gt;. FRP was originally invented in the 1990s by Conal Elliott in the context of Haskell, but almost twenty years later, has finally spread well beyond that now to mainstream visibility and use. For example, Microsoft has thrown its weight behind &lt;a href=&#34;http://rx.codeplex.com/&#34;&gt;Reactive Extensions (Rx)&lt;/a&gt;, which started out in the .NET world, but Microsoft then ported it to JavaScript, C/C++, Python, and Ruby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:4a05566a34ea27820d7f737863a690ea&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was happy to see interest in functional programming in the local JavaScript community. Richard gave an introductory talk on it that I thought was very useful as a starting point for those who are new to it. I made note of some omissions or inaccuracies in order to improve my thinking about how I can contribute in the future to improving people&amp;rsquo;s understanding and application of functional programming principles.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning about Parasail: a new parallel programming language</title>
      <link>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2012/10/17/learning-about-parasail-a-new-parallel-programming-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2012 20:39:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2012/10/17/learning-about-parasail-a-new-parallel-programming-language/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I noticed an announcement for a talk to be given at CMU for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isri.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;ISR&lt;/a&gt; by visitor Tucker Taft, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/afs/.cs.cmu.edu/Web/copetas/Posters/ISR-Taft12.pdf&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;ParaSail: A Pointer-Free Path to Object-Oriented Parallel Programming&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and decided to attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d recognized &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Optikos/S._Tucker_Taft&#34;&gt;Tucker Taft&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s name because decades ago (and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.adacore.com/company/about/executive-team/&#34;&gt;now still&lt;/a&gt;), he was a very prominent member of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ada_%28programming_language%29&#34;&gt;Ada programming language&lt;/a&gt; community, being one of the primary designers of the extensions to the original Ada 83. I never actually used Ada 95, but was following it a little bit because in 1995 I had to maintain some Ada 83 code at work, so I was curious where Ada was going. (I haven&amp;rsquo;t used Ada since leaving that job in 1997.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was curious what an Ada guy had in mind as for one of the next steps in programming language design (parallelism), and why a new language and how it would be informed by an Ada mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;parasail-and-why-a-new-language-anyway:277903bcdd4917269c8c2ab8eefc7e73&#34;&gt;Parasail, and why a new language anyway?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new language Taft has been working on is called Parasail and &lt;a href=&#34;http://parasail-programming-language.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;its Web site is really a blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why a new language, and not, say, libraries and idioms to bolt onto an existing language? Because to make parallelism &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; to program, and correctly, language support is the way to go, leveraging types and compiler knowledge to help programmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a new thought, of course. Parallel languages have been designed and implemented for decades. But none can be said to have truly caught on universally in practice. For example, as a graduate student in the late 1990s, I learned and used &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~guyb/&#34;&gt;Guy Blelloch&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~scandal/nesl.html&#34;&gt;NESL&lt;/a&gt;, based on the functional language &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_ML&#34;&gt;Standard ML&lt;/a&gt;, and I briefly participated in exploring bringing the ideas from NESL back into ML itself, as part of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.cmu.edu/~pscico/&#34;&gt;PSciCo project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.haskell.org/haskellwiki/GHC/Data_Parallel_Haskell&#34;&gt;Data Parallel Haskell&lt;/a&gt; is another example of an attempt at a very high level parallel programming language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these languages all come from the functional programming world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mutation:277903bcdd4917269c8c2ab8eefc7e73&#34;&gt;Mutation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently the goal of Parasail is to not force programmers to go all out into functional programming. For both style and efficiency, it may be desirable to program imperatively, with mutation. So how does Parasail try to cope with all the potential problems caused by mutation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parasail bans pointers, hiding them from the programmer by using types. In particular, assignment is by copy, but move and swap semantics are used underneath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;memory-management:277903bcdd4917269c8c2ab8eefc7e73&#34;&gt;Memory management&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, garbage collection is avoided through &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Region-based_memory_management&#34;&gt;region-based memory management&lt;/a&gt;. This is an old idea, of course: I remember experimenting with using MLKit from the 1990s by Tofte and Talpin when it was hot off the press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-examples:277903bcdd4917269c8c2ab8eefc7e73&#34;&gt;Code examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taft gave some code examples to illustrate paralellization in Parasail. For example, quicksort is important because of its use of mutation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-features:277903bcdd4917269c8c2ab8eefc7e73&#34;&gt;Other features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt; is intentionally a sync point that introduces nondeterminism. Also, underneath, work stealing is used to handle the threads used underneath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:277903bcdd4917269c8c2ab8eefc7e73&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting to see new work on parallel programming languages. Check out Parasail&amp;rsquo;s Web site if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in learning more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>