<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: c++ | The Conscientious Programmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/categories/c-plus-plus/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-08T22:54:23-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Franklin Chen]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[franklinchen@franklinchen.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[toString considered harmful, part 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/27/tostring-considered-harmful-part-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T22:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/27/tostring-considered-harmful-part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is part 3 of a series of articles, &ldquo;<code>toString</code> considered harmful&rdquo;.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Languages without the <code>toString</code> problem</h2>

<p>There actually are quite a few languages that don&rsquo;t have the <code>toString</code> problem, or at least have it to a lesser degree.</p>

<h3>C</h3>

<p>There is no friendly generic conversion to a string (uh, really just a pointer to a null-terminated chunk of <code>char</code>) in C. The closest thing is using the type-unsafe <code>printf</code> family of functions, but you have to do almost all the work if you have some complicated <code>struct</code> and want to turn it into a C string.</p>

<h3>C++</h3>

<p>C++ introduced iostreams, where f you follow certain conventions and overload <code>operator&lt;&lt;</code> for every domain class of interest, you can build up decent looking strings, without using inheritance.</p>

<p>Or you could do the object-oriented thing and set up a hierarchy with a <code>ToString</code> abstract base class. But C++ does not come with everything already inheriting from an <code>Object</code>.</p>

<h3>Haskell</h3>

<p>Haskell does not force a <code>toString</code> on everything, but provides a <a href="http://www.haskell.org/tutorial/stdclasses.html"><code>Show</code> type class</a> for convenience in the standard prelude. It is easy (and convenient for debugging) to just tack on <code>deriving Show</code> and then call <code>show</code> to convert stuff to a string. This means that one can get lazy and fall into the same design traps as mentioned in the very first code example above. Again, the solution is to refuse to abuse <code>show</code>, and to use a different name instead for converting something to a string for a particular purpose.</p>

<h3>Go</h3>

<p>Go was invented at Google as a modernized C. It does not have classes, but does have <a href="http://research.swtch.com/interfaces">dynamic interfaces</a>. All that is required for a user-defined type to satisfy an interface is to implement the method <code>String()</code> returning a <code>string</code>. Basically, this makes the type implement the interface <a href="http://golang.org/pkg/fmt/#Stringer">fmt.Stringer</a>. Again, if you don&rsquo;t implement <code>String() string</code> for your type, then you will get a compile-time error when trying to treat it as a string.</p>

<p>Superficially, this sounds like Haskell type classes, but it&rsquo;s much more limited, because Go does not have generics and Go is only single dispatch. Go&rsquo;s interfaces really implement a kind of structural subtyping.</p>

<h3>Standard ML</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.standardml.org/">Standard ML</a> does not have the <code>toString</code> problem. It does, by convention, supply a <code>toString</code> function in many modules in the <a href="http://www.standardml.org/Basis/">Standard ML Basis Library</a>, such as <a href="http://www.standardml.org/Basis/integer.html">Int</a> and <a href="http://www.standardml.org/Basis/real.html">Real</a> and <a href="http://www.standardml.org/Basis/bool.html">Bool</a>, but these are just conventions and do not participate in any kind of unified conversion to string. If you want to convert anything besides a primitive type to a string, you have to write the conversion function yourself.</p>

<p>Furthermore, Standard ML, as a rather opinionated and <a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/books/definition-standard-ml">&ldquo;purist&rdquo; language</a>, designed specifically for static simplicity, semantic minimalism, and <a href="http://mlton.org/">runtime efficiency</a>, does not believe in type classes, so there is no way to write a function that at runtime is generic over what can be turned into a string.</p>

<p>The best you can do is write something that is functorized, but then you have to apply it in a statically known context:</p>

<pre><code class="sml">signature TO_STRING =
  sig
    type t
    val toString : t -&gt; string
  end

functor DoStuff(ToString : TO_STRING) =
  struct
    fun doubleString (stuff: ToString.t) =
      let
        val s = ToString.toString stuff
      in
        s ^ s
      end
  end

structure MyStuff : TO_STRING =
  struct
    type t = int * bool
    fun toString (i, b) =
      "(" ^ Int.toString i ^ ", " ^ Bool.toString b ^ ")"
  end

structure DoMyStuff = DoStuff(MyStuff)
</code></pre>

<p>with</p>

<pre><code class="sml">DoMyStuff.doubleString (42, true)
(* result is the string "(42, true)(42, true)" *)
</code></pre>

<p>Since the Standard ML ecosystem is so minimalist, it&rsquo;s hard to fall into the <code>toString</code> trap, because you would have to set it all up yourself.</p>

<h3>OCaml</h3>

<p>OCaml, like Standard ML, does not provide a generic <code>toString</code> out of the box, but the OCaml ecosystem is much more practically oriented.</p>

<p>There is a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camlp4">pre-processor for OCaml</a> that can be used to generate convenient printers for types, <a href="https://github.com/ocsigen/deriving"><code>deriving</code></a>. There is also an S-expression based generator, <a href="http://realworldocaml.org/v1/en/html/data-serialization-with-s-expressions.html">Sexplib</a>. But these are mechanically generated, rather than part of something generic at runtime.</p>

<p>Of course, one could also use the <a href="http://caml.inria.fr/pub/docs/manual-ocaml-4.01/objectexamples.html">object-oriented part of OCaml</a> to make a generic &ldquo;to string&rdquo; hierarchy starting with a suitable interface:</p>

<pre><code class="ocaml">class type convert_to_string =
  object
    method to_string : string
  end
</code></pre>

<p>But I don&rsquo;t actually know many people who use the object-oriented features of OCaml!</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>An annoying bug I temporarily created in my code led me to take stock of the state of <code>toString</code> design choices in various programming languages, and also consider how we can better escape fragility in our code, independent of whatever language we are using.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[toString considered harmful, part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/26/tostring-considered-harmful-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-26T22:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/26/tostring-considered-harmful-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is part 2 of a series of articles, &ldquo;<code>toString</code> considered harmful&rdquo;. [Part 1] introduced the problem in the context of a common design flaw present in object-oriented languages, and proposed a simple workaround.</p>

<p>In part 2, we look at advanced ways to organize &ldquo;stringable&rdquo; data, using either an object-oriented or functional style. Examples are in Scala because it equally supports either style.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Object-oriented vs. functional</h2>

<p>The fix presented was in <em>object-oriented</em> style, adding a method <code>toUrlString</code> to a class. The other solution is the <em>functional</em> style, leaving the <code>Id</code> class alone, and writing an external function instead:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  case class Id(id: Int)

  def toUrlString(id: Id) = id.toString
</code></pre>

<p>with</p>

<pre><code class="scala">    id match {
      case None =&gt; println("No id found!")
      case Some(n) =&gt; getUrl(makeUrl(toUrlString(n)))
    }
</code></pre>

<p>There are advantages and disadvantages to either solution.</p>

<h2>More advanced OO</h2>

<p>It would be very natural, given a whole set of domain classes in addition to <code>Id</code>, to want all of them to have a <code>toUrlString</code>. Then the natural thing to do is to create a mini-universe (parallel to the <code>toString</code> universe) by creating a hierarchy:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  trait UrlString {
    def toUrlString: String
  }

  case class Id(id: Int) extends UrlString {
    override def toUrlString = id.toString
  }

  case class ...(...) extends UrlString {
    override def toUrlString = ...
  }
</code></pre>

<h2>Advanced string interpolation with OO</h2>

<p>In fact, Scala and other languages with advanced string interpolation facilities allow yet another refactoring by making sure that what gets into a URL isn&rsquo;t just an arbitrary string in the first place!</p>

<p>Below we define a string interpolator that only operates on objects of classes that implement the trait <code>UrlString</code>, and therefore does away with an explicit call to <code>toUrlString</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  implicit class UrlHelper(val sc: StringContext) extends AnyVal {
    def url(args: UrlString*): String = {
      val strings = sc.parts.iterator
      val expressions = args.iterator
      val buf = new StringBuffer(strings.next)
      while (strings.hasNext) {
        buf append expressions.next.toUrlString
        buf append strings.next
      }
      buf.toString
    }
  }

  /** Only ever use UrlString to create a URL. */
  def makeUrl(id: UrlString): String = url"http://service.com?id=$id"
</code></pre>

<p>with</p>

<pre><code class="scala">    id match {
      case None =&gt; println("No id found!")
      case Some(n) =&gt; getUrl(makeUrl(n))
    }
</code></pre>

<p>This may or may not be overengineering.</p>

<h2>Advanced string interpolation with FP</h2>

<p>The functional approach doesn&rsquo;t like inheritance in the domain classes. We can implement it with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Type_class">type classes</a> (a concept first pioneered in Haskell in the late 1980s) by means of implicits in Scala, in order to implement <code>toUrlString</code> outside of a class hierarchy but also allow it to be used in a constrained generic way. A full discussion of this is outside the scope of this post, but the basic point is that with type classes, one can write code that does <em>not</em> depend on an inheritance hierarchy. If you&rsquo;re used to monkey-patching in dynamic languages, think of it as compile-time monkey-patching.</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  // A type class
  trait UrlString[A] {
    def toUrlString(a: A): String
  }

  // Wrapper class
  case class Id(id: Int)

  // Implement the type class UrlString for Id
  implicit object IdToUrlString extends UrlString[Id] {
    override def toUrlString(a: Id) = a.id.toString
  }

  implicit class UrlHelper(val sc: StringContext) extends AnyVal {
    def url[A: UrlString](args: A*): String = {
      val strings = sc.parts.iterator
      val expressions = args.iterator
      val buf = new StringBuffer(strings.next)
      while (strings.hasNext) {
        buf append implicitly[UrlString[A]].toUrlString(expressions.next)
        buf append strings.next
      }
      buf.toString
    }
  }

  /** Anything "viewable" as UrlString can be used to create a URL. */
  def makeUrl[A: UrlString](id: A): String = url"http://service.com?id=$id"
</code></pre>

<h2>The final string gotcha</h2>

<p>You may have noticed that there is still primitive obsession in this sample code: URLs are presented as <code>String</code> for simplicity. In real life, I use builders such as <code>URIBuilder</code> and <code>HttpGet</code> (Java <a href="http://hc.apache.org/">Apache HttpComponents</a>) or more sophisticated Scala-specific libraries such as <a href="http://spray.io/">Spray</a>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I thought it would useful to compare an object-oriented and a functional approach to unifying data that share a domain-consistent notion of conversion to a string. Scala is a language that allows easy expression of both.</p>

<p>In part 3, we will look at languages that just don&rsquo;t have the <code>toString</code> problem at all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[toString considered harmful, part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/23/tostring-considered-harmful-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-23T23:54:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/23/tostring-considered-harmful-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is easy to rant about the problems or unexpected subtleties involving the use of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/String_%28computer_science%29">strings</a> in programming languages. This post, however, is not so much a rant about strings as about design and meaning, with <code>toString</code> only as an obvious example.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll describe a pitfall that came up in my code, and a solution, and make observations about how different programming languages address or avoid this problem.</p>

<p>This is part one of a series.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>A bug when evolving my code</h2>

<p>My example code is in Scala, but the problem illustrated actually extends to many (most?) other currently popular object-oriented languages as well, including Java (which Scala inherited <code>Object.toString</code> from), C# (<code>Object.ToString</code> stolen from Java), Ruby (<code>Object#to_s</code>), Python (<code>str</code>, which uses <code>object.__str__</code> in case of an object). (Later in the post, I discuss languages without this specific feature.)</p>

<h3>First working code</h3>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the first version of the code, which is a simplification of logic in a real application. A name is looked up to find an ID, then the ID is used to construct a URL to submit to a Web service.</p>

<pre><code class="scala">object Example {
  type Id = Int

  /**
    @param name User name to look up
    @return ID of user
    */
  def findId(name: String): Id =
    if (name == "name") {
      42
    } else {
      0
    }

  def makeUrl(id: Id): String = s"http://service.com?id=$id"

  /** Simulate making the Web request. */
  def getUrl(url: String): Unit = println(url)

  def main(args: Array[String]): Unit = {
    val id = findId("name")
    getUrl(makeUrl(id))
    // output: http://service.com?id=42
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>In this code, everything seems fine. This was the situation in my application when it was certain that finding an ID would succeed.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t know Scala, just note that <code>s"...$id"</code> is just Scala&rsquo;s string interpolation syntax that behind the scenes calls <code>id.toString</code>.</p>

<h3>Non-working code</h3>

<p>It turned out that finding an ID could fail, so I changed <code>findId</code> to return the type <code>Option[Id]</code> instead of <code>Id</code>. To get the code to compile, I had to change the type of the parameter to <code>makeUrl</code> also:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  /**
    @param name User name to look up
    @return Some(ID of user) if found, else None
    */
  def findId(name: String): Option[Id] =
    if (name == "name") {
      Some(42)
    } else {
      None
    }

  // Oops, now this has an unintended bug!
  def makeUrl(id: Option[Id]): String = s"http://service.com?id=$id"
</code></pre>

<p>But this resulted in a bug (thankfully caught by my test suite that actually went over the Web to fetch stuff)! The bug was that the URL constructed was nothing resembling what I ever wanted to construct: <code>http://service.com?id=Some(42)</code> was being requested.</p>

<p>Furthermore, in the case of an ID not found, the URL constructed is <code>http://service.com?id=None</code>. How many of you have seen applications or Web sites or emails in which something was clearly missing and the text contained either an empty space or the string &ldquo;null&rdquo; or &ldquo;nullvalue&rdquo; such as</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Dear NULL,</p></p><p><p>You ordered NULL items.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Yup, you guessed it: someone wrote crappy code like what I just showed you, and frightening thing is, <em>it could have been me</em> and <em>it could have been you</em>.</p>

<h4>What&rsquo;s the big deal?</h4>

<p>You might think, &ldquo;Big deal, you changed your code, ran your test, and immediately found the bug, so what&rsquo;s the problem?&rdquo;</p>

<p>The problem is that I have higher standards than that. I don&rsquo;t want to rely on my tests to find my bugs. In fact, the test that went over the Web to do stuff was an <em>integration test</em>, not a <em>unit test</em>. The bug only manifested itself when the actual Web request failed. And as we see in real life, many apps are not sufficiently tested to root out all possible accidental string generations.</p>

<p>So although I caught the bug quickly, I caught it far less quickly than I wanted. I didn&rsquo;t want to even construct an obviously garbage URL like <code>http://service.com?id=Some(42)</code> at all. I prefer to have the type checker catch stupid design-level bugs up front. So I was furious at myself that I wrote code that the compiler was perfectly happy with but was obviously wrong. I had gotten lazy in more ways than one, and had been punished accordingly.</p>

<h2>A symptom of bad design</h2>

<p>There were a couple of things wrong with my original code that made it not evolve well.</p>

<h3>Don&rsquo;t use <code>toString</code></h3>

<p>First, by using string interpolation at all, I was relying on the implicit <code>toString</code> method of all objects. String interpolation is an admittedly very convenient feature that I use extensively, but now I consider it rather dangerous.</p>

<p>But even if I hadn&rsquo;t used string interpolation, I would have had to build up strings myself anyway, and would have called <code>toString</code> <em>explicitly</em>, and I would have had the same problem: changing the type of something from <code>Id</code> to <code>Option[Id]</code> does not get rid of <code>toString</code>. In fact, in object-oriented languages where <code>toString</code> is defined way up at the top, <em>everything</em> has <code>toString</code>, whether you like it or not! The best you can do is override <code>toString</code>. (Actually, Scala &ldquo;helpfully&rdquo; generates a nice <code>toString</code> override for you when you use case classes, hence the output of <code>Some(42)</code>.)</p>

<p>I consider this <em>global infection</em> a flaw in object-oriented languages that impose a set of methods on all objects whether you want them or not. <code>toString</code> is hardly the worst offending method, actually, but I&rsquo;ll save my complaints about others for later.</p>

<p>First step in cleaning up the code: make <code>toString</code> explicit:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  /** Only ever use a String to create a URL. */
  def makeUrl(id: String): String = s"http://service.com?id=$id"

  def main(args: Array[String]): Unit = {
    val id = findId("name")
    getUrl(makeUrl(id.toString))
  }
</code></pre>

<p>(Later in the post, I will discuss alternatives to this explicit <code>toString</code>.)</p>

<h3>Primitive obsession</h3>

<p>Another design smell was that of using</p>

<pre><code class="scala">type Id = Int
</code></pre>

<p>in the first place. This is a well-known lazy practice called <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?PrimitiveObsession">primitive obsession</a>. I know better than that.</p>

<p>The solution to primitive obsession is easy: create a new wrapper type. Hence, the original code, even before the possibly failing ID lookup, should have been</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  case class Id(id: Int)

  /**
    @param name User name to look up
    @return ID of user
    */
  def findId(name: String): Id =
    if (name == "name") {
      Id(42)
    } else {
      Id(0)
    }
</code></pre>

<p>Note that this still <em>would not</em> have solved the <code>toString</code> problem, since the output would simply have been <code>http://service.com?id=Some(Id(42))</code> or the dreaded <code>http://service.com?id=None</code>!</p>

<h3><code>toString</code> is a problematic concept anyway</h3>

<p>The real problem is one that transcends programming language design. (Later in this post I&rsquo;ll show languages that don&rsquo;t have <code>toString</code> but still easily allow a similar problem.)</p>

<p>The real problem is that strings are used for <em>multiple</em> purposes. Some are used just for debugging, showing an internal representation of data. Some are used for &ldquo;human&rdquo; reading. In fact, many languages distinguish between these two purposes: Lisp has <a href="http://www.lispworks.com/documentation/HyperSpec/Body/f_wr_pr.htm"><code>write</code>, <code>prin1</code>, <code>print</code>, <code>pprint</code></a>; Scheme has <a href="http://www.scheme.com/tspl3/io.html"><code>write</code> and <code>display</code></a>; Ruby has <a href="http://ruby-doc.org/core-2.0.0/Object.html"><code>to_s</code> and <code>to_str</code></a>; Python has <a href="http://docs.python.org/2/library/functions.html"><code>repr</code> and <code>str</code></a>.</p>

<p>One is often directed to override the &ldquo;human-oriented&rdquo; version of these mechanisms (implementing one&rsquo;s own special non-default format). In Java and Scala, that&rsquo;s <code>toString</code>. But this is precisely the problem. We are <em>encouraged</em> to abuse this built-in mechanism for getting a string from an object that is supposed to mean something in the <em>context of an application</em>. Yes, <code>Some(Id(42))</code> is a useful human-readable string, but it&rsquo;s not what I want to put into a URL for an ID parameter!</p>

<h4>Different names for different contexts</h4>

<p>Suppose you had a <code>Name</code> class, and it had fields such as <code>first</code> and <code>middle</code> and <code>last</code>. It&rsquo;s nonsensical to expect a single <code>toString</code> override to express all the different contexts in which you might want to get a single string from a full name. Sometimes you might want to generate <code>Franklin Chen</code>; other times, <code>Franklin Ming Chen</code>; other times, <code>Franklin M. Chen</code>; other times, <code>FMC</code>. The point is that there should really be a method for each of these. <code>toString</code> should be treated really as a debugging device.</p>

<p>Instead of piggybacking on <code>toString</code>, we should call a spade a spade, and define our own methods whose name is actually informative and tells us for what <em>purpose</em> we are asking for a string.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s refactor the code:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  // Wrapper class
  case class Id(id: Int) {
    // Special method for turning to URL string fragment
    def toUrlString = id.toString
  }

  /**
    @param name User name to look up
    @return Some(ID of user) if found, else None
    */
  def findId(name: String): Option[Id] =
    if (name == "name") {
      Some(Id(42))
    } else {
      None
    }

  /** Only ever use a String to create a URL. */
  def makeUrl(id: String): String = s"http://service.com?id=$id"

  /** Simulate making the Web request. */
  def getUrl(url: String): Unit = println(url)

  def main(args: Array[String]): Unit = {
    val id = findId("name")
    // Will not compile because Option[Id] does not have toUrlString
    //getUrl(makeUrl(id.toUrlString))
  }
</code></pre>

<p>Now the code that was creating a junk URL will no longer compile: <code>id</code> is of type <code>Option[Id]</code> but that type does <em>not</em> have a <code>toUrlString</code> method. Mission accomplished!</p>

<p>To fix the code to get it compile, we handle both the case in which the ID is not found and the case in which it is:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">    // Will not compile because Option[Id] does not have toUrlString
    //getUrl(makeUrl(id.toUrlString))

    id match {
      case None =&gt; println("No id found!")
      case Some(n) =&gt; getUrl(makeUrl(n.toUrlString))
    }
</code></pre>

<p>Simple!</p>

<h2>The final string gotcha (to be discussed later)</h2>

<p>You may have noticed that there is still primitive obsession in this sample code: URLs are presented as <code>String</code> for simplicity. In real life, I use builders such as <code>URIBuilder</code> and <code>HttpGet</code> (Java <a href="http://hc.apache.org/">Apache HttpComponents</a>) or more sophisticated Scala-specific libraries.</p>

<p>However, at some point, data has to be turned into strings: this simply is how the Web works. It is at that point where one has to watch out. I will discuss that boundary in another post. String injection attacks are precisely a result of being sloppy about crossing that boundary.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I gave a small taste of what the <code>toString</code> problem is about, and some initial steps toward solving it through better design even if the programming language encourages us to be sloppy.</p>

<p>In part 2 of this series, I will expand on different design choices even in the situation we just examined, especially in the face of continued evolution in which there are multiple domain classes to be turned into strings.</p>

<p>Finally, there actually are quite a few languages that don&rsquo;t have this particular <code>toString</code> problem, but some have analogues to a lesser degree. Part 3 of this series will discuss the different design choices in the languages or in the standard libraries or idioms. Examples will be drawn from C, C++, Haskell, Go, Standard ML, OCaml, Rust, and JavaScript.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenHack Pittsburgh: learning Elixir test-driven and package-publishing]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/08/26/openhack-pittsburgh-learning-elixir-test-driven-and-package-publishing/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-26T22:09:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/08/26/openhack-pittsburgh-learning-elixir-test-driven-and-package-publishing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a long time since I went to an <a href="http://openhack.github.io/pittsburgh/">OpenHack Pittsburgh</a> meeting. The last time was <a href="http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/25/openhack-pittsburgh-exploring-scala-odds-and-ends/">five months ago</a>. On June 24, there was an <a href="http://www.meetup.com/pittsburgh-ruby/events/120200292/">OpenHack Pittsburgh</a> held at <a href="http://www.4moms.com/">4moms</a>, but I really needed to stay home and take it easy that evening, because of my busy schedule later in the week, including attending a <a href="/blog/2013/06/25/pittsburgh-java-user-group-building-and-evolving-a-java-api/">PittJUG meeting</a> and preparing a <a href="/blog/2013/06/26/pittsburgh-python-night-of-the-favorite-module/">Pittsburgh Python talk</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.meetup.com/pittsburgh-ruby/events/120201842/">This August meeting of OpenHack Pittsburgh</a> was held at <a href="http://www.modcloth.com/">ModCloth</a>, which I had never been to. It&rsquo;s in Crafton, which is a place I&rsquo;ve never been before, nearly half an hour drive from Pittsburgh. Because of worries about driving there near rush hour after work, I probably would not have signed up to attend had it not been for <a href="http://justinxreese.com/">Justin</a>, the organizer of OpenHack Pittsburgh.</p>

<p>What happened was that he asked for feedback about who was planning to work on what, and said he planned to learn some <a href="http://elixir-lang.org/">Elixir</a>, a fairly new programming language built on top of the <a href="http://www.erlang.org/">Erlang</a> runtime. Since this language had been on my list of things to look into, I decided that learning loves company, so I proposed to learn some Elixir in a test-driven way!</p>

<p>What does that mean?</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://distilleryimage10.ak.instagram.com/1e5597280ea711e3b2db22000aeb1b88_7.jpg">http://distilleryimage10.ak.instagram.com/1e5597280ea711e3b2db22000aeb1b88_7.jpg</a>" title="Franklin working on laptop" ></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>How to learn a programming language</h2>

<p>I have written code in probably around fifty (50) programming languages. I&rsquo;m not kidding, and I&rsquo;m not proud, but this is simply a fact of my having done programming since 1982, thirty-one (31!!) years ago. Let&rsquo;s face it: languages come and go. I have personally sat at an IBM <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keypunch">keypunch</a> machine punching out cards for my COBOL and Fortran code.</p>

<p>As with human languages, the fact is that to be truly productive in a language requires much more than learning some syntax and semantics. It requires actually writing and running and fixing code, and in the context of a realistic project.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve learned through trial and error that the most common ways of learning a programming language, like the most common ways of learning human languages (other than one&rsquo;s first language), are terribly inefficient and misleading, resulting in minimal competence. I mean, reading through books, typing into a REPL, submitting a single file to a compiler or interpreter, etc.</p>

<p>I feel that we should learn programming languages using a variety of approaches. Yes, the academic bottom-up semantics-based approach is critical in the long run, to avoid wasting a lot of time on pointless misunderstandings. Exploration in a REPL can be very rewarding. But I think what is often missing is the <em>biggest possible picture</em>: immediately seeing how to write a program that is integrated with a test framework, uses libraries, is exportable and publishable publicly as a library, can be submitted to a continuous integration server, is editable in a decent editor or IDE, etc.</p>

<p>Without seeing the biggest possible picture, one usually gets a horribly inaccurate picture of what it is like to program in a particular language ecosystem. (I will be writing more about this subject of pedagogy later.)</p>

<h2>My proposal</h2>

<p>The last couple of languages I have learned in recent years, I slowly came to work with in a more efficient way than in the past, because I focused on matters such as testability. In particular, as I grew to wholly adopt TDD when writing any code at all in any language, it became clear to me that the best way to learn a new language must be in a test-driven way.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s an analogy: I believe the best way to learn a human language is to dive into how to be able to converse in some coherent way right off the bat. <a href="http://www.fluentin3months.com/4-hour/">Tim Ferriss and others</a> have exploited this idea to <em>drive</em> the learning of what is most relevant in <a href="http://www.fourhourworkweek.com/blog/2007/11/07/how-to-learn-but-not-master-any-language-in-1-hour-plus-a-favor/">grammar</a> and <a href="http://www.fourhourworkweek.com/blog/2009/01/20/learning-language/">vocabulary</a>.</p>

<p>In the past, I learned human languages in a terrible way, taking lots of courses, but never actually getting fluent in everyday use. This is how we tend to learn &ldquo;foreign&rdquo; programming languages. My proposal is that learning a new programming language should involve getting as quickly as possible up to speed on a <em>minimum viable publishable library</em>.</p>

<p>That the software artifact should be a <em>library</em>, and not just some executable program, is vital, because it means having to adhere by whatever standards apply to real-world API design in the language ecosystem, producing something that client code can import and call.</p>

<p>That it should be <em>publishable</em> is vital because it means adhering to standards of testing, of discovery through metadata, and enabling easy use by a client.</p>

<h2>My concrete example with learning Elixir tonight</h2>

<h3>Prior background in Erlang and Elixir</h3>

<p>I went to OpenHack Pittsburgh <em>never</em> having yet read any Elixir language material, never having written Elixir code, not even &ldquo;hello, world&rdquo;. The only things I had done before tonight:</p>

<ul>
<li>I first heard of Erlang nearly two decades ago, and when I saw it, I was turned off by the Prolog-style syntax, and it didn&rsquo;t seem relevant to anything I was doing at the time, so I ignored it.</li>
<li>I intended to learn some Erlang earlier this year, but made little progress before putting it aside: I went to the free book <a href="http://learnyousomeerlang.com/">&ldquo;Learn You Some Erlang for Great Good!&rdquo;</a> and downloaded the code and <a href="https://github.com/FranklinChen/learn-you-some-erlang">got it to compile</a>, but did not proceed any further.</li>
<li>I installed Elixir on my Mac <a href="http://elixir-lang.org/getting_started/1.html">using Homebrew</a>.</li>
<li>I installed an <a href="https://github.com/elixir-lang/emacs-elixir">Emacs Elixir mode</a>.</li>
<li>I made a note of a free online book <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1234000001642">&ldquo;Etudes for Elixir&rdquo;</a> and checked out the GitHub repository, but did not look at the book or code.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Find a testing framework</h3>

<p>Upon arrival at ModCloth, getting pizza to eat, and plugging in my MacBook and connecting to the guest WiFi, the first thing I did was search for a testing framework for Elixir.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s 2013, not 1993, so it is hard to convince me to invest any time at all in learning to operate in a language ecosystem that does not have at least a de facto standard testing framework. For every language that I currently actively use for writing serious programs, I operate with TDD. Some examples of languages and the test frameworks I currently use for them:</p>

<ul>
<li>C/C++: <a href="https://code.google.com/p/googletest/">googletest</a></li>
<li>Clojure: <a href="https://github.com/marick/Midje">Midje</a></li>
<li>Haskell: <a href="http://hspec.github.io/">HSpec</a> and <a href="http://www.haskell.org/haskellwiki/Introduction_to_QuickCheck2">QuickCheck</a></li>
<li>Java or Scala: <a href="http://specs2.org/">Specs2</a> and <a href="http://www.scalacheck.org/">ScalaCheck</a></li>
<li>JavaScript: <a href="http://pivotal.github.io/jasmine/">Jasmine</a></li>
<li>Perl: <a href="http://search.cpan.org/~mschwern/Test-Simple-0.98/lib/Test/More.pm">Test::More</a></li>
<li>Python: <a href="http://pytest.org/">pytest</a></li>
<li>Ruby: <a href="http://rspec.info/">RSpec</a></li>
<li>Racket: <a href="http://docs.racket-lang.org/rackunit/">RackUnit</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Well, first Web search hit for Elixir and unit testing was <a href="http://elixir-lang.org/getting_started/ex_unit/1.html">ExUnit</a>, so that was encouraging.</p>

<p>Justin was still stuck installing Elixir, so we started exploring Elixir together off my laptop.</p>

<h3>One test file</h3>

<p>The first thing I did after discovering ExUnit was to copy and paste the code for a sample test into Emacs and save it into a file <code>test_hello.exs</code>, see that the Elixir mode was working (with syntax highlighting), and figure out how to run the test: <code>$ elixir test_hello.exs</code>.</p>

<p>It worked!</p>

<p>Then we explored adding more tests, changing some assertions, and learning as went, by looking up the Elixir documentation. For example, Elixir uses an interesting callback mechanism for cleanly passing &ldquo;setup&rdquo; state to tests inside a single test case. Also, <code>assert</code> and <code>test</code> are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macro_%28computer_science%29#Syntactic_macros">syntactic macros</a>, enabling them to do magic to analyze expressions, hence the support of natural assertion syntax (which <a href="/blog/2013/07/11/pittsburgh-ruby-lightning-talk-night/">I like a lot better than special syntax</a>).</p>

<p>After writing some failing tests involving arithmetic and making them pass, I wrote a division by zero test. I was intrigued that not only did it fail, as expected, but also the compiler warned ahead of time that an exception was going to be raised. Nice. In any case, I learned how to make an assertion of the raising of an exception. This is very important. We should always pay attention to <a href="http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/06/01/report-on-the-second-pittsburgh-techfest-2013/">testing the sad paths</a>.</p>

<p>We saw in the documentation for ExUnit that there was a way to mark a test case as being OK to run concurrently with others. Great! These days there is no excuse not to be able to run tests concurrently. So I wrote another test case, which I put in the same source file (for the moment), and I wanted to see for myself that concurrency was happening. I wanted to call some kind of &ldquo;sleep&rdquo; function. To do that, I did a Web search, and found that Erlang comes with <code>sleep</code> in the <code>timer</code> module. I found out how to call Erlang from Elixir, and it worked!</p>

<h3>More than one source file</h3>

<p>The next obvious step was to write a test for code that did not yet exist, but was to be written outside the test source file. For that, I had to figure out how to define a module and import it. OK, but then there&rsquo;s the question of file organization. Hmm.</p>

<p>At this point, the only reasonable thing to do (and which in retrospect should have been done first) was to find out what the &ldquo;standard&rdquo; way of organizing a project&rsquo;s source files is supposed to be, and what the standard way to build everything is.</p>

<p>A Web search quickly came up with <a href="http://elixir-lang.org/getting_started/mix/1.html">Mix</a>. Awesome, the Elixir people are serious about real software development! Mix turns out to be inspired by Clojure&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/technomancy/leiningen">Leiningen</a>, which of course I use to start any new Clojure project. <code>$ mix new hello</code> did the trick, creating the scaffolding for a new Elixir project.</p>

<p>I refactored our existing <code>test_hello.exs</code> file into two files (one for each test case) in the <code>test</code> directory, then wrote a module <code>hello.ex</code> into <code>lib</code>. A failed test, then making it succeed, and finally I wrote my first non-test code in Elixir!</p>

<p>Running tests is very easy once you are using Mix. Just <code>$ mix test</code> does it.</p>

<h3>Packaging for publshing</h3>

<p>At this point, I decided I wanted to create an actual Elixir package to publish.</p>

<p>So I did a Web search to find out whether there was a standard repository and how to publish to it.</p>

<p>Here we go, <a href="http://expm.co/">Expm</a>!</p>

<p>I installed the package manager, set up my user name and password, and went to work on a simple package to publish.</p>

<p>I saw that nobody had yet contributed an implementation of <a href="http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/14/for-real-geeks-today-is-not-pi-day-but-half-tau-day/">tau</a>, so I quickly created a tau library with Mix, did <code>$ expm new</code> to create a <code>package.exs</code> template, filled it out, wrote an ExUnit test that passed, completed the <code>README.md</code>, and just as OpenHack Pittsburgh was officially closing for the evening, I successfully published <a href="http://expm.co/tau">my tau package</a>!</p>

<p>Actually, I accidentally screwed up the first time, forgetting to change all the fields of the template <code>package.exs</code> and ending up published <code>yourlib</code>.</p>

<p>Oh, and I committed my project in Git and pushed <a href="https://github.com/franklinchen/tau">to GitHub</a>.</p>

<h2>Some Haskell stuff</h2>

<p>Steve McCarthy of <a href="http://www.spacefinity.com/">Spacefinity</a> had announced, in the introduction at the beginning of the evening when each of us stood up to say what we planned to work on, that he wanted to do more with the <a href="http://www.haskell.org/cabal/">Cabal</a> package manager for Haskell, so I spent a little bit of time getting him going by pointing him toward a sample Haskell code repository I initially <a href="http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/05/the-start-of-a-local-haskell-study-group.markdown/">set up last year when some friends were interested in getting into Haskell</a>; sadly, we&rsquo;ve all been too busy for Haskell, so I&rsquo;ve let the project rot, in the sense that my configuration file is not optimally organized and also there have been updates in the test framework world in Haskell since then.</p>

<p>Anyway, here&rsquo;s my <a href="https://github.com/FranklinChen/project-euler-haskell">&ldquo;Project Euler in Haskell&rdquo; repository</a>. I plan to get around to improving it.</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Thanks to ModCloth for providing the space, pizza, cookies, and WiFi!</p>

<p>A big thank-you to Justin for providing the inspiration for me to try this experiment in learning!</p>

<p>And thanks to Steve McCarthy for getting me to drag up an old Haskell project and making me think that I should soon update it to be a better example.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Tonight was the first time I ever started learning a new programming language, wrote unit tests right off the bat with proper project organization and also published a library immediately.</p>

<p>Of course, there is much more to go in actually really learning and using Elixir, but as a first step in showing that Elixir has a viable ecosystem, I think the experiment was a success. My next steps in continuing to learn Elixir would include writing tests in conjunction with a deep dive into the actual semantics of the language. There is no substitute for the latter; the alternative is dangerously making assumptions based on superficial syntactic similarity with other languages (such as Ruby).</p>

<h3>(Update of 2013-08-27)</h3>

<p>One thing I didn&rsquo;t get around to was setting up <a href="http://travis-ci.org/">Travis</a> continuous integration. I believe this should also be part of the story in getting up and running in a new programming language environment.</p>

<p>So I did a Web search and figured out how to create a suitable <code>.travis.yml</code>. I committed and pushed to GitHub, flipped the switch in my Travis account, and you can see its <a href="https://travis-ci.org/FranklinChen/tau">passing status</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pittsburgh Ruby/Python social and some observations about our polyglot world]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/08/02/pittsburgh-ruby-python-social/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-02T22:17:42-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/08/02/pittsburgh-ruby-python-social</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Programming meetups aren&rsquo;t just about presentations and coding. Abby and I joined others in meeting up for dinner for a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/pittsburgh-ruby/events/120201652/">joint Pittsburgh Ruby and Pittsburgh Python social</a> and enjoyed relaxing and socializing outdoors in Bakery Square. Although it perpetually looked like it was going to rain, it turned out we weren&rsquo;t really rained on.</p>

<!-- http://instagram.com/p/ch8quus4Kb/ -->


<p><img class="<a" src="href="http://distilleryimage11.ak.instagram.com/31a91496fbd111e2996722000a9f18fe_7.jpg">http://distilleryimage11.ak.instagram.com/31a91496fbd111e2996722000a9f18fe_7.jpg</a>" title="Dinner outside" ></p>

<!-- https://secure.flickr.com/photos/carolnichols/9425969330/ -->




<iframe src="https://www.flickr.com/photos/carolnichols/9425969330/player/" width="75" height="75" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>It was fitting that there was a joint social for two language communities, because we live in a polyglot world.</p>

<p>Despite my original intention not to engage into any tech-related conversation, I couldn&rsquo;t help remarking on my current polyglot responsibilities at work at CMU on the METAL project!</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Our polyglot world: Ruby, Python, Perl</h2>

<p>I mentioned having to cobble together Ruby, Python, and Perl code recently in an NLP project to process Farsi text into corpora to analyze. We used a Ruby gem <a href="https://github.com/aziz/virastar">Virastar</a> in our pipeline, a Perl script for a Farsi stemmer, <a href="http://perstem.sourceforge.net/">Perstem</a>, and a <a href="https://github.com/wfeely/farsiNLPTools">Python script for normalization</a>.</p>

<h3>(Update of 2013-12-04) C++, Scala, MongoDB</h3>

<p>The work project ended up becoming even more polyglot than I expected.</p>

<p>I also used a C++ tagger, TurboTagger from <a href="http://www.ark.cs.cmu.edu/TurboParser/">TurboParser</a>.</p>

<p>I wrote Scala to execute and monitor the pipeline, because it turned out that component bugs and timeouts (from infinite loops sometimes) had to be dealt with: the original shell script pipelines did not handle any of that at all. Also, the vast amount of data meant that parallelizing was critical. The Scala ecosystem has  turned out great for me. I didn&rsquo;t use Akka actors for this task, just futures and parallel collections.</p>

<p>I also used MongoDB because it is quite a natural fit for document-oriented storage and querying as an intermediate stage I can inspect before the final stage of conversion to Sketch Engine format. And I happened to just <a href="/blog/2013/12/04/mongodb-free-online-course-a-review/">finish a free online MongoDB course</a> which has been useful. In my Scala code, I used the official Scala driver <a href="https://github.com/mongodb/casbah">Casbah</a>.</p>

<p>Why MongoDB? I needed to track the transformations, and experiment with different parameters while also fixing bugs and rerunning stuff. Because there is so much data and sometimes something crashes in the pipeline, I decided to save all intermediate results in a database in order to avoid repeating work.</p>

<p>Finally, I used Scala to generate corpora for importing into <a href="http://www.sketchengine.co.uk/">The Sketch Engine</a> for our Farsi linguistics experts to analyze. Scala&rsquo;s parser combinator library came in very useful, and I represented each stage in the pipeline as a transformation of a custom AST designed to finally serialize well to the Sketch Engine &ldquo;vert&rdquo; file format.</p>

<p>It was pretty important to work with ASTs, since we actually got text in a variety of formats, which I parsed to a common AST in order to push into the pipeline.</p>

<p>Whew!</p>

<h3>(Update of 2014-06-10)</h3>

<p>A description of some of this <a href="http://springfield.metaphor.cs.cmu.edu:8080/MetaphorViz/About.html">METAL project</a> work is in the paper <a href="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2014/pdf/596_Paper.pdf">&ldquo;The CMU METAL Farsi NLP Approach&rdquo;</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
