<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pittsburgh Code And Supply on The Conscientious Programmer</title>
    <link>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/categories/pittsburgh-code-and-supply/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pittsburgh Code And Supply on The Conscientious Programmer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2014 21:10:18 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/categories/pittsburgh-code-and-supply/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Code and Supply: Making music with Overtone in Clojure; Conveying information through sound</title>
      <link>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2014/10/07/pittsburgh-code-and-supply-making-music-with-overtone-in-clojure-conveying-information-through-sound/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2014 21:10:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2014/10/07/pittsburgh-code-and-supply-making-music-with-overtone-in-clojure-conveying-information-through-sound/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I attended &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/202086812&#34;&gt;a fine meeting&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codeandsupply.co/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Code and Supply&lt;/a&gt; dedicated to two related topics: &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;sonification&lt;/em&gt;. I thought it was a great idea to have presentations on both topics in the same session, thereby giving a broad view of what can be done with &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; through computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;erik-swanson-on-overtone-in-clojure:eae2c8db91585e112346d13d734d08c3&#34;&gt;Erik Swanson on Overtone in Clojure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://overtone.github.io/&#34;&gt;Overtone&lt;/a&gt; is a very interesting environment for programmable music written in Clojure that I&amp;rsquo;d heard of years ago but never gotten around to playing with, simply because my primary interest in music is &lt;a href=&#34;http://franklinchen.com/categories/music/&#34;&gt;playing music on traditional physical instruments with my own hands, the old-fashioned way&lt;/a&gt;. However, I am definitely open to the idea of doing interesting new things with computer aid; it just has not been a priority to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As preparation for the presentation (I don&amp;rsquo;t like feeling completely lost during live demos; I usually do!), I actually finally set up an Overtone project with Leiningen and walked through a tutorial that simply used the Clojure CIDER mode in Emacs to operate in a REPL. I didn&amp;rsquo;t do any real live-coding, however. I just wanted to get a taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erik Swanson gave a great presentation in which he described what he was doing as he live-coded some music with Emacs, incrementally creating instruments and generating pitches. Because of his presentation, I feel more comfortable about the prospect of really digging into Overtone if I ever want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a video of his presentation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/w7ARayiKBrE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;keith-callenberg-https-twitter-com-keithcallenberg-on-conveying-information-through-sound:eae2c8db91585e112346d13d734d08c3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/keithcallenberg&#34;&gt;Keith Callenberg&lt;/a&gt; on conveying information through sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a new word today: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonification&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;sonification&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, the use of non-speech audio to convey information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may have vaguely encountered sonification before, but never while fully attentive to it. That changed when Keith Callenberg, a computational scientist, gave a fine presentation in which he gave numerous striking examples of sonification. He made the important distinction between music and sonification: music is sound for an aesthetic purpose, but sonification is for information transfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He convincingly showed why sonification is useful for data analysis, and also noted that our culture is strangely dominated by the &lt;em&gt;visual&lt;/em&gt;, so there remain many opportunities to use sound to understand data. (Also, sonification is used to help the visually impaired.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One local example he gave was a particulate monitoring study done at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;david-souther-on-web-audio-in-javascript:eae2c8db91585e112346d13d734d08c3&#34;&gt;David Souther on Web Audio in JavaScript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought we were done for the evening, but David Souther hopped up with an unscheduled lightning talk on using Web Audio in JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:eae2c8db91585e112346d13d734d08c3&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the presentations on music and sound, and got some ideas for stuff I might want to do myself. Another excellent session for Pittsburgh Code and Supply!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Code and Supply: Programming in journalism</title>
      <link>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2014/07/17/pittsburgh-code-and-supply-programming-in-journalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2014 21:21:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2014/07/17/pittsburgh-code-and-supply-programming-in-journalism/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://static.squarespace.com/static/538f3cc8e4b00f52172b5560/t/53a4ec76e4b0488fb14c5a29/1403317372203/sign.png?format=500w&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I finally attended my first ever &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codeandsupply.co/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Code and Supply&lt;/a&gt; meeting! The group, which posts its &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/&#34;&gt;events on Meetup&lt;/a&gt;, was created by local Pittsburgh software developer &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/justinxreese&#34;&gt;Justin Reese&lt;/a&gt; just a few months ago, in March 2014. His vision is to create a local community that, unlike conventional specific language/technology-based meetups, is much more universal and broad. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t do so already, read more about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codeandsupply.co/about&#34;&gt;goals of Pittsburgh Code and Supply&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m very excited about this new group!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Code and Supply meetup I just attended was about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/186766512/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Programming in journalism&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. This is a topic of huge importance, and I was excited to attend to hear more about what some local journalist/programmers are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-bit-about-sponsors:5ceb897fd4e46960a338a7fd3d6cf4e6&#34;&gt;A bit about sponsors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Justin opened by briefly saying a few words about the goals of Pittsburgh Code and Supply. He then noted that this month, the group did not have sponsors, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pittsburgh Code and Supply needs sponsors!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like what Code and Supply is doing, please consider seeing if your employer would be willing to step up as a sponsor for the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;contribute:5ceb897fd4e46960a338a7fd3d6cf4e6&#34;&gt;Contribute!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, in any case, spread the word about the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first meeting, and next Monday, I am actually going to give my first presentation for the group, on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/183483622/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Type-Directed TDD in Rust&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. The group is always looking for people to speak about something or facilitate other formats of meetings, so &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codeandsupply.co/speak/&#34;&gt;sign up&lt;/a&gt; if you have an idea! I personally have some ideas I&amp;rsquo;d like to propose for future meetings, such as discussions about technology-related topics such as philosophy, history, and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;amyjo-brown:5ceb897fd4e46960a338a7fd3d6cf4e6&#34;&gt;AmyJo Brown&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/DaOxhNkHvvw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://amyjobrown.com/&#34;&gt;AmyJo Brown&lt;/a&gt;, an independent journalist, gave a great talk about the kind of work that she does, and why it is important. She gave an overview of how journalism has changed because of the availability of data and because of the complexity of the world, both of which lead to the necessity of telling stories differently, as evidenced by what &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.propublica.org/&#34;&gt;ProPublica&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/&#34;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.latimes.com/&#34;&gt;Los Angeles Times&lt;/a&gt; have been doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her own work involves tracking political donations (&amp;ldquo;follow the money&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She gave examples of software tools she uses to get data, clean it, analyze it, and archive the whole process. On the programming end, she programs in Python, for example (Django for Web development), and uses &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.documentcloud.org/&#34;&gt;DocumentCloud&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She talked about many things to keep in mind while doing this kind of data journalism. First of all, you have to know the limitations of the data you&amp;rsquo;re getting. She has to deal with handwritten documents, and data in different formats. Data that is clearly incomplete or entered wrong (whether accidentally or maliciously). It is necessary to know the domain, know the context in which data was collected or required or submitted, to not fall into the trap of just blindly treating data as a record of the full truth and just get into programmatically processing it. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot that involves human judgment calls. And this is why it is so important to save all the original information and document each step of data &amp;ldquo;cleaning&amp;rdquo; and interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near the end of her talk, AmyJo had her colleague Katrina speak a bit also. Katrina was not originally trained as a programmer, but was always interested in politics. She ended up getting into programming later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I&amp;rsquo;m always very excited and impressed to hear of people with domain knowledge and passion who take up computer programming as a useful skill to apply to their domain. Sometimes I hear people saying &amp;ldquo;please don&amp;rsquo;t code&amp;rdquo;; I totally disagree with this sentiment and believe that &lt;a href=&#34;http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/09/why-everyone-should-learn-computer-science/&#34;&gt;everyone can benefit from learning the fundamentals of computer science and programming&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;andrew-mcgill:5ceb897fd4e46960a338a7fd3d6cf4e6&#34;&gt;Andrew McGill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/0iT9rhwRXVs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrewrmcgill.com/&#34;&gt;Andrew McGill&lt;/a&gt; bills himself as &amp;ldquo;your friendly neighborhood journalist&amp;rdquo;, and works for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He started by talking about his interesting career path, which involved being into computers before college, but then going to college and then finding other interests and abandoning programming, and then only later taking it back up, in the service of journalism, to enable him to find data and tell stories through visualization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He showed us specific Web sites and articles he has created to provide better visualizations of data than what is available in raw form. For example, on the funny side, there is &lt;a href=&#34;http://newsinteractive.post-gazette.com/wheresbill/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Where&amp;rsquo;s Bill?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which he created because he was not happy with the &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; boring text news feed of Mayor Bill Peduto&amp;rsquo;s calendar. He scraped the official site with PHP. He also created a Bill Peduto Twitter bot using Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also showed a D3-based visualization of &lt;a href=&#34;http://newsinteractive.post-gazette.com/plugged-wells/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Mystery of the Plugged Wells&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Again, the point was to take already available data but to tell a story better with it than just giving raw tables or a purely text-based narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He showed some other projects, such as a visualization of school comparisons based on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pennsylvania_System_of_School_Assessment&#34;&gt;PSSA&lt;/a&gt; data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions-and-answers:5ceb897fd4e46960a338a7fd3d6cf4e6&#34;&gt;Questions and answers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were quite a lot of questions posed to the presenters throughout the evening, on the technologies used, on work with graphic designers, on the process of obtaining data, and political implications of the work. Great discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;technologies-used:5ceb897fd4e46960a338a7fd3d6cf4e6&#34;&gt;Technologies used&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s something resembling a summary of technologies mentioned that the presenters use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Django&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DocumentCloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Git&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SQL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;D3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;interesting-articles:5ceb897fd4e46960a338a7fd3d6cf4e6&#34;&gt;Interesting articles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the meetup, I posted to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/186766512/&#34;&gt;event page&lt;/a&gt; a link to a provocative (perhaps too harsh and ranty) article warning about dangers in data journalism, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.niemanlab.org/2014/07/alberto-cairo-data-journalism-needs-to-up-its-own-standards/&#34;&gt;by visualization expert Alberto Cairo&lt;/a&gt;. It got no response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, I also posted a link to a thoughtful examination of the question of &lt;a href=&#34;http://source.opennews.org/en-US/learning/true-facts-maybe/&#34;&gt;epistemology in data journalism&lt;/a&gt;. I totally recommend reading that article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AmyJo after the meetup posted some more links on the event page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@jeremybowers/why-im-a-newsroom-coder-860d9d49f684&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why I&amp;rsquo;m a newsroom coder&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/planting-next-crop-newsroom-coders/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Planting the next crop of newsroom coders&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/17/opinion/the-fec-lags-on-campaign-finance-disclosures.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Data delayed is democracy denied&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:5ceb897fd4e46960a338a7fd3d6cf4e6&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very excited to attend my first Pittsburgh Code and Supply meetup, on the fascinating topic of programming in journalism. I felt I learned a lot about what is at stake and how programming is being used in journalism to better inform people of what is going on in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Scala Meetup: Exploring type-directed, test-driven development using FizzBuzz (my practice talk)</title>
      <link>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2014/05/15/pittsburgh-scala-meetup-exploring-type-directed/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2014 22:49:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2014/05/15/pittsburgh-scala-meetup-exploring-type-directed/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Scala-Meetup/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Scala Meetup&lt;/a&gt; met, with me presenting a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Scala-Meetup/events/146581402/&#34;&gt;practice talk&lt;/a&gt; for &amp;ldquo;Exploring type-directed, test-driven development using FizzBuzz&amp;rdquo;, which I am presenting at the upcoming local &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghtechfest.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh TechFest&lt;/a&gt; conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;presentation:0ca97438327f3bcfe743d5a186e4af3e&#34;&gt;Presentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only recently completed the slides and code for my talk, and had not actually given the talk yet, so this was a practice talk that did not go so well, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spoke too quickly and had too much material to cover, and also got lost in some of my own slides. Oops. I think reaction to my talk was mixed. Some enjoyed it, while others seemed lost at places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After going home, I frankly felt that I had &lt;em&gt;failed&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I believe I can do much better. I have plenty of time to do a thorough revision before Pittsburgh TechFest in three weeks. I need to cut out material that is not needed for the core of what I am trying to achieve and make some things clearer (especially for the intended Pittsburgh TechFest audience, which I do not expect to even know Scala).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;supporting-material:0ca97438327f3bcfe743d5a186e4af3e&#34;&gt;Supporting material&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/FranklinChen/talk-on-type-directed-tdd-using-fizzbuzz&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t recommend looking at them, but for historical purposes, here are slides of the presentation &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/FranklinChen/talk-on-type-directed-tdd-using-fizzbuzz/blob/meetup/doc/presentation.pdf&#34;&gt;as it was given in the first draft&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-05-16:0ca97438327f3bcfe743d5a186e4af3e&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-05-16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day makes a difference in my confidence and determination! I noticed that the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Code and Supply&lt;/a&gt; group (which I have not yet attended) is soon having its inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rust-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/181773312/&#34;&gt;soon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided to offer to do a version of my talk for Pittsburgh Code and Supply using Rust as the programming language (rather than Scala). I want to spread the news about how to effectively use a sufficiently typed programming language, whether it&amp;rsquo;s Scala or Rust or anything else sufficiently derived from the ML family of type systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Justin will schedule it for some time in July. That should give me enough time, after Pittsburgh TechFest in early June, to learn enough Rust to convert my Scala code over properly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-06-07:0ca97438327f3bcfe743d5a186e4af3e&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-06-07)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I much improved the presentation for Pittsburgh TechFest, which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/06/07/report-on-the-2014-pittsburgh-techfest-my-third-year/&#34;&gt;attended for the third year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend reading the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/FranklinChen/talk-on-type-directed-tdd-using-fizzbuzz/blob/master/doc/article.pdf&#34;&gt;article version of the presentation&lt;/a&gt;, rather than the slides. This is the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve created both an article version of a presentation and slides for use during the live presentation. I will do this in the future as well. Slides are not meant to stand alone or even be read alone, but in case you really want to see them, they are here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/37257104&#34; width=&#34;427&#34; height=&#34;356&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; style=&#34;border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom:5px&#34;&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/FranklinChen/presentation-37257104&#34; title=&#34;Exploring type-directed, test-driven development: a case study using FizzBuzz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Exploring type-directed, test-driven development: a case study using FizzBuzz&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/FranklinChen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Franklin Chen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-17:0ca97438327f3bcfe743d5a186e4af3e&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s crunch time. My Rust version of the talk, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/183483622/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Type-Directed TDD in Rust&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; is coming next week.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>