<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rust | The Conscientious Programmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/categories/rust/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-22T02:55:26-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Franklin Chen]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[franklinchen@franklinchen.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to think about Rust ownership versus C++ unique_ptr]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2014/12/21/how-to-think-about-rust-ownership-versus-c-plus-plus-unique-ptr/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-21T14:31:36-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2014/12/21/how-to-think-about-rust-ownership-versus-c-plus-plus-unique-ptr</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.rust-lang.org/">Rust</a> programming language, which is nearing its important version 1.0 release, but already seen a lot of use, has many interesting features, the most prominent of which is its <a href="http://doc.rust-lang.org/guide.html#ownership,-borrowing,-and-lifetimes">ownership</a> static type system that prevents certain kinds of bugs common in many programs in C or C++.</p>

<p>For example, it is common in most applications to create graphs of objects pointing to each other, in which it is not clear how many pointers point to a particular object, who is to free the object&rsquo;s memory when it is no longer needed, and what happens to all outstanding pointers to that block. Languages supporting precise <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garbage_collection_%28computer_science%29">garbage collection</a> use various algorithms to determine when memory can be freed, and have become particularly popular in the past twenty years, but there are still situations in which garbage collection is not ideal, hence the continued relevance of languages such as C++.</p>

<p>When I was working as a software engineer in the 1990s developing desktop applications with user interfaces for the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X_Window_System">X Window System</a>, we used frameworks that included C++ <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smart_pointer">smart pointers</a> that used <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reference_counting">reference counting</a> to handle graphs of interconnected data. The C++ standard itself lagged behind in standardizing smart pointers; it started with the <a href="http://www.informit.com/articles/article.aspx?p=30642&amp;seqNum=9">terribly flawed and unusable</a> <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auto_ptr"><code>auto_ptr</code></a> that finally got deprecated in C++11, then moved on finally to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smart_pointer#unique_ptr"><code>unique_ptr</code></a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smart_pointer#shared_ptr_and_weak_ptr"><code>shared_ptr</code> and <code>weak_ptr</code></a>.</p>

<p>When talking with C++ programmers about Rust, I have found that often they have been puzzled about how Rust&rsquo;s ownership system does anything better than what C++ <code>unique_ptr</code> already does. Here is an explanation (I will not be discussing analogues of <code>shared_ptr</code> and <code>weak_ptr</code> here).</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Simplest example: compile-time type-checking vs. run-time segmentation fault</h2>

<p>First, go read Steve Klabnik&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.steveklabnik.com/uniq_ptr_problem/">article about the simplest possible example illustrating what Rust offers over C++ <code>unique_ptr</code></a>.</p>

<p>Basically, in C++, <code>unique_ptr</code> is supposed to be a way to indicate that a given pointer is the unique &ldquo;owner&rdquo; of a piece of data. If you want to transfer ownership from one <code>unique_ptr</code> to another, you have to call <code>move</code> on it. After that, it is an <em>run-time error</em> to try to access the data using the original <code>unique_ptr</code>. This is great, except for two things:</p>

<ul>
<li>By &ldquo;it&rsquo;s a run-time error&rdquo;, we mean that the original <code>unique_ptr</code>&rsquo;s embedded pointer gets mutated to <code>nullptr</code>, so that you have to perpetually check your <code>unique_ptr</code> for <code>nullptr</code>, otherwise get a segmentation fault.</li>
<li>In many situations, we&rsquo;d prefer to have a <em>compile-time</em> guarantee that we will never dereference <code>nullptr</code>, so that we don&rsquo;t have hidden memory safety bugs lying around in our code that don&rsquo;t happen until well into a long-running program.</li>
</ul>


<p>Here is Steve&rsquo;s example of an unintended segmentation fault from C++:</p>

<pre><code class="c++">#include &lt;iostream&gt;
#include &lt;memory&gt;

using namespace std;

int main ()
{
    unique_ptr&lt;int&gt; orig(new int(5));

    cout &lt;&lt; *orig &lt;&lt; endl;

    auto stolen = move(orig);

    cout &lt;&lt; *orig &lt;&lt; endl;
}
</code></pre>

<p>Steve shows an &ldquo;equivalent&rdquo; Rust program in which code attempts to move ownership fails to compile because of a type error (I edited to correspond more closely with the C++):</p>

<pre><code class="rust">fn main() {
    let orig = box 5i;

    println!("{}", *orig);

    let stolen = orig;

    println!("{}", *orig);
}
</code></pre>

<h2>Understanding C++ behavior by modeling it in Rust, safely</h2>

<p>But it is not quite accurate to call the Rust program &ldquo;equivalent&rdquo; to the original C++ program. It&rsquo;s really a &ldquo;cleaned up&rdquo; or &ldquo;restricted&rdquo; version of that program (and the argument for using a type-safe language like Rust is that we often like these restrictions, as a tradeoff for safety or efficiency).</p>

<p>Here is a Rust program that more accurately models what the C++ <code>unique_ptr</code> actually does, which happens <em>dynamically</em> at run-time, not at compile time, hence the segmentation fault: the transfer of ownership by <code>move</code> on a <code>unique_ptr</code> is not type-checked at compile-time.</p>

<p>For illustration&rsquo;s sake, we have modeled C++ directly in <em>safe</em> Rust through indirection by treating a C++ pointer to <code>T</code> (C++ pointers can always be <code>nullptr</code>) as an <code>Option&lt;Box&lt;T&gt;&gt;</code>, where <code>nullptr</code> is modeled as <code>None</code> and a non-null pointer is modeled as <code>Some(pointer_nonnull)</code>. This Rust code type-checks, compiles, and simulates a segmentation fault.</p>

<p>You can play with this code <a href="http://is.gd/5kEQA8">at this Rust playground link</a>. (You may find it interesting to examine the assembly code generated.)</p>

<pre><code class="rust">// Simulate a segmentation fault.
fn seg_fault() {
    panic!("segmentation fault");
}

fn main() {
    // Rough modeling in Rust of C++ unique_ptr&lt;int&gt;
    // because C++ pointers can always be null.
    let mut orig: Option&lt;Box&lt;int&gt;&gt; = Some(box 5i);

    match orig {
        // In C++, deferencing null seg faults.
        None =&gt; seg_fault(),
        Some(orig_nonnull) =&gt; {
            println!("{}", *orig_nonnull);

            // The equivalent of C++ unique_ptr move.
            let stolen = Some(orig_nonnull);
            orig = None;

            match orig {
                // We seg fault after the C++ style move.
                None =&gt; seg_fault(),
                Some(orig_nonnull) =&gt; println!("{}", *orig_nonnull)
            }
        }
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Nobody would ever write this kind of code in Rust, but implicitly, all C++ programs are semantically basically doing this, except that for efficiency, the <code>nullptr</code> checking is not done at the language level but just results in an actual segmentation fault at the operating system level.</p>

<h2>An example of smart pointers inside a collection</h2>

<p>The single most disturbing failure mode of the C++-based software product I worked on in 1995-1997 in C++ was segmentation faults resulting from mysteriously disappearing pointers. What I mean is, behavior like the following, where a container containing smart pointers to objects was meant to <em>own</em> them, but there was no compile-time way to verify this fact, because of the nature of the object graph. If someone didn&rsquo;t play by the uncheckable rules and inadvertently took ownership of (instead of &ldquo;borrowing&rdquo; through a raw pointer) something embedded in the collection, then <code>nullptr</code> appeared, and a segmentation fault happened.</p>

<pre><code class="c++">#include &lt;vector&gt;
#include &lt;memory&gt;
#include &lt;iostream&gt;

using namespace std;

int main() {
    vector&lt;unique_ptr&lt;int&gt;&gt; v;
    v.push_back(make_unique&lt;int&gt;(5));

    cout &lt;&lt; *v[0] &lt;&lt; endl;

    // C++ happily allows this.
    auto pointer_to_5 = move(v[0]);
    cout &lt;&lt; *pointer_to_5 &lt;&lt; endl;

    // Seg fault.
    cout &lt;&lt; *v[0] &lt;&lt; endl;
}
</code></pre>

<p>You can probably guess what some developers did to &ldquo;fix&rdquo; the segmentation fault. They started adding <code>nullptr</code> checks everywhere to prevent crashing, but this only resulted in <em>corrupt user data and documents</em>, because in fact, we lost data in those collections and smart pointers to the data should never have ended up <code>nullptr</code>!!</p>

<p>The complexity of the application and the deadline pressures made it impossible to fully figure out what was going wrong and where. I actually ended up writing an external &ldquo;validation&rdquo; utility program in <a href="http://www.smlnj.org/">Standard ML of New Jersey</a> that parsed serialized object graphs and tried to fix them up in some fashion. This particularly helped the QA team a lot when dealing with old documents that were already corrupted.</p>

<h3>The Rust version will not compile</h3>

<p>The Rust type-checker rejects any attempt to move ownership out of a collection. (Try to compile it in <a href="http://is.gd/Om7wfr">this playground</a>.)</p>

<pre><code class="rust">fn main() {
    let v = vec![box 5i];

    println!("{}", *v[0]);

    // Attempted move: type error at compile time.
    let pointer_to_5 = v[0];
    println!("{}", *pointer_to_5);

    println!("{}", *v[0]);
}
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="console">illegal_move_out_of_vector.rs:7:24: 7:28 error: cannot move out of dereference (dereference is implicit, due to indexing)
illegal_move_out_of_vector.rs:7     let pointer_to_5 = v[0];
                                                       ^~~~
illegal_move_out_of_vector.rs:7:9: 7:21 note: attempting to move value to here
illegal_move_out_of_vector.rs:7     let pointer_to_5 = v[0];
                                        ^~~~~~~~~~~~
</code></pre>

<h3>Often, you do want to share</h3>

<p>I have to be honest: at first, Rust&rsquo;s ownership type system seems like quite a restriction, and adhering to it strictly would require the restructuring of certain kinds of programs. Static type safety of any kind in any language is always a matter of tradeoffs.</p>

<p>But note that Rust is flexible: you don&rsquo;t have to use Rust&rsquo;s default pointer type! You can use one of Rust&rsquo;s many other pointer types, such as <a href="http://doc.rust-lang.org/guide.html#rc-and-arc"><code>Rc</code> or <code>Arc</code></a>, that allow reference-counted shared ownership (like C++ <code>shared_ptr</code>), if that&rsquo;s what you really want. (<a href="http://is.gd/HNi7SR">Playground here</a>.)</p>

<pre><code class="rust">// Reference-counted smart pointer.
use std::rc::Rc;

fn main() {
    let v = vec![Rc::new(5i)];

    println!("{}", *v[0]);

    let pointer_to_5 = v[0].clone();
    println!("{}", *pointer_to_5);

    println!("{}", *v[0]);
}
</code></pre>

<h2>Unsafe</h2>

<p>Finally, Rust does allow you to go all out and write <a href="http://doc.rust-lang.org/guide.html#unsafe">unsafe</a> code, if you truly need to for raw C performance or FFI reasons. Most of the time you do not need to, because the whole point of Rust is to compile down to the same kind of assembly code you would get from C.</p>

<pre><code class="rust">extern crate libc;

use libc::{size_t, malloc};
use std::mem;
use std::ptr;

fn main() {
    // How ugly it is to pretend Rust is unsafe C.
    unsafe {
        let mut orig: *mut int = malloc(mem::size_of::&lt;int&gt;() as size_t)
            as *mut int;
        ptr::write(&amp;mut *orig, 5i);

        println!("{}", *orig);

        orig = ptr::null::&lt;int&gt;() as *mut int;

        // null pointer crash!
        println!("{}", *orig);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I hope this little article shows a little bit about what Rust&rsquo;s ownership type system can do to make pointer-heavy code memory safe, unlike C++, and also gives you a taste of how Rust&rsquo;s flexibility also allows you to use C++-style reference-counting if desired, and even raw unsafe code. Personally, I am excited about the upcoming 1.0 release of Rust, and although I have not done low-level systems programming for almost two decades, if I ever was to do it again, I would immediately reach out for Rust as a language of choice for the ultimate combination of safety, expressiveness, and performance (in use of time and space).</p>

<p>All code for this article is available in a <a href="https://github.com/FranklinChen/rust-vs-cpp-unique_ptr">GitHub repository</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pittsburgh Scala Meetup: Exploring type-directed, test-driven development using FizzBuzz (my practice talk)]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2014/05/15/pittsburgh-scala-meetup-exploring-type-directed/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-15T22:49:48-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2014/05/15/pittsburgh-scala-meetup-exploring-type-directed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Scala-Meetup/">Pittsburgh Scala Meetup</a> met, with me presenting a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Scala-Meetup/events/146581402/">practice talk</a> for &ldquo;Exploring type-directed, test-driven development using FizzBuzz&rdquo;, which I am presenting at the upcoming local <a href="http://pghtechfest.com/">Pittsburgh TechFest</a> conference.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Presentation</h2>

<p>I have only recently completed the slides and code for my talk, and had not actually given the talk yet, so this was a practice talk that did not go so well, unfortunately.</p>

<p>I spoke too quickly and had too much material to cover, and also got lost in some of my own slides. Oops. I think reaction to my talk was mixed. Some enjoyed it, while others seemed lost at places.</p>

<p>After going home, I frankly felt that I had <em>failed</em>.</p>

<p>But I believe I can do much better. I have plenty of time to do a thorough revision before Pittsburgh TechFest in three weeks. I need to cut out material that is not needed for the core of what I am trying to achieve and make some things clearer (especially for the intended Pittsburgh TechFest audience, which I do not expect to even know Scala).</p>

<h2>Supporting material</h2>

<p>Here is the <a href="https://github.com/FranklinChen/talk-on-type-directed-tdd-using-fizzbuzz">GitHub repository</a>.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t recommend looking at them, but for historical purposes, here are slides of the presentation <a href="https://github.com/FranklinChen/talk-on-type-directed-tdd-using-fizzbuzz/blob/meetup/doc/presentation.pdf">as it was given in the first draft</a>.</p>

<h2>(Update of 2014-05-16)</h2>

<p>One day makes a difference in my confidence and determination! I noticed that the new <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/">Pittsburgh Code and Supply</a> group (which I have not yet attended) is soon having its inaugural <a href="http://www.rust-lang.org/">Rust</a> <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/181773312/">soon</a>.</p>

<p>So I decided to offer to do a version of my talk for Pittsburgh Code and Supply using Rust as the programming language (rather than Scala). I want to spread the news about how to effectively use a sufficiently typed programming language, whether it&rsquo;s Scala or Rust or anything else sufficiently derived from the ML family of type systems.</p>

<p>Justin will schedule it for some time in July. That should give me enough time, after Pittsburgh TechFest in early June, to learn enough Rust to convert my Scala code over properly!</p>

<h2>(Update of 2014-06-07)</h2>

<p>I much improved the presentation for Pittsburgh TechFest, which I <a href="/blog/2014/06/07/report-on-the-2014-pittsburgh-techfest-my-third-year/">attended for the third year</a>.</p>

<p>I recommend reading the <a href="https://github.com/FranklinChen/talk-on-type-directed-tdd-using-fizzbuzz/blob/master/doc/article.pdf">article version of the presentation</a>, rather than the slides. This is the first time I&rsquo;ve created both an article version of a presentation and slides for use during the live presentation. I will do this in the future as well. Slides are not meant to stand alone or even be read alone, but in case you really want to see them, they are here:</p>

<iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/37257104" width="427" height="356" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p> <div style="margin-bottom:5px"> <strong> <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/FranklinChen/presentation-37257104" title="Exploring type-directed, test-driven development: a case study using FizzBuzz" target="_blank">Exploring type-directed, test-driven development: a case study using FizzBuzz</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/FranklinChen" target="_blank">Franklin Chen</a></strong> </div></p>

<h2>(Update of 2014-07-17)</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s crunch time. My Rust version of the talk, <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/183483622/">&ldquo;Type-Directed TDD in Rust&rdquo;</a> is coming next week.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[toString considered harmful, part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/23/tostring-considered-harmful-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-23T23:54:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/23/tostring-considered-harmful-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is easy to rant about the problems or unexpected subtleties involving the use of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/String_%28computer_science%29">strings</a> in programming languages. This post, however, is not so much a rant about strings as about design and meaning, with <code>toString</code> only as an obvious example.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll describe a pitfall that came up in my code, and a solution, and make observations about how different programming languages address or avoid this problem.</p>

<p>This is part one of a series.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>A bug when evolving my code</h2>

<p>My example code is in Scala, but the problem illustrated actually extends to many (most?) other currently popular object-oriented languages as well, including Java (which Scala inherited <code>Object.toString</code> from), C# (<code>Object.ToString</code> stolen from Java), Ruby (<code>Object#to_s</code>), Python (<code>str</code>, which uses <code>object.__str__</code> in case of an object). (Later in the post, I discuss languages without this specific feature.)</p>

<h3>First working code</h3>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the first version of the code, which is a simplification of logic in a real application. A name is looked up to find an ID, then the ID is used to construct a URL to submit to a Web service.</p>

<pre><code class="scala">object Example {
  type Id = Int

  /**
    @param name User name to look up
    @return ID of user
    */
  def findId(name: String): Id =
    if (name == "name") {
      42
    } else {
      0
    }

  def makeUrl(id: Id): String = s"http://service.com?id=$id"

  /** Simulate making the Web request. */
  def getUrl(url: String): Unit = println(url)

  def main(args: Array[String]): Unit = {
    val id = findId("name")
    getUrl(makeUrl(id))
    // output: http://service.com?id=42
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>In this code, everything seems fine. This was the situation in my application when it was certain that finding an ID would succeed.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t know Scala, just note that <code>s"...$id"</code> is just Scala&rsquo;s string interpolation syntax that behind the scenes calls <code>id.toString</code>.</p>

<h3>Non-working code</h3>

<p>It turned out that finding an ID could fail, so I changed <code>findId</code> to return the type <code>Option[Id]</code> instead of <code>Id</code>. To get the code to compile, I had to change the type of the parameter to <code>makeUrl</code> also:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  /**
    @param name User name to look up
    @return Some(ID of user) if found, else None
    */
  def findId(name: String): Option[Id] =
    if (name == "name") {
      Some(42)
    } else {
      None
    }

  // Oops, now this has an unintended bug!
  def makeUrl(id: Option[Id]): String = s"http://service.com?id=$id"
</code></pre>

<p>But this resulted in a bug (thankfully caught by my test suite that actually went over the Web to fetch stuff)! The bug was that the URL constructed was nothing resembling what I ever wanted to construct: <code>http://service.com?id=Some(42)</code> was being requested.</p>

<p>Furthermore, in the case of an ID not found, the URL constructed is <code>http://service.com?id=None</code>. How many of you have seen applications or Web sites or emails in which something was clearly missing and the text contained either an empty space or the string &ldquo;null&rdquo; or &ldquo;nullvalue&rdquo; such as</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Dear NULL,</p></p><p><p>You ordered NULL items.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Yup, you guessed it: someone wrote crappy code like what I just showed you, and frightening thing is, <em>it could have been me</em> and <em>it could have been you</em>.</p>

<h4>What&rsquo;s the big deal?</h4>

<p>You might think, &ldquo;Big deal, you changed your code, ran your test, and immediately found the bug, so what&rsquo;s the problem?&rdquo;</p>

<p>The problem is that I have higher standards than that. I don&rsquo;t want to rely on my tests to find my bugs. In fact, the test that went over the Web to do stuff was an <em>integration test</em>, not a <em>unit test</em>. The bug only manifested itself when the actual Web request failed. And as we see in real life, many apps are not sufficiently tested to root out all possible accidental string generations.</p>

<p>So although I caught the bug quickly, I caught it far less quickly than I wanted. I didn&rsquo;t want to even construct an obviously garbage URL like <code>http://service.com?id=Some(42)</code> at all. I prefer to have the type checker catch stupid design-level bugs up front. So I was furious at myself that I wrote code that the compiler was perfectly happy with but was obviously wrong. I had gotten lazy in more ways than one, and had been punished accordingly.</p>

<h2>A symptom of bad design</h2>

<p>There were a couple of things wrong with my original code that made it not evolve well.</p>

<h3>Don&rsquo;t use <code>toString</code></h3>

<p>First, by using string interpolation at all, I was relying on the implicit <code>toString</code> method of all objects. String interpolation is an admittedly very convenient feature that I use extensively, but now I consider it rather dangerous.</p>

<p>But even if I hadn&rsquo;t used string interpolation, I would have had to build up strings myself anyway, and would have called <code>toString</code> <em>explicitly</em>, and I would have had the same problem: changing the type of something from <code>Id</code> to <code>Option[Id]</code> does not get rid of <code>toString</code>. In fact, in object-oriented languages where <code>toString</code> is defined way up at the top, <em>everything</em> has <code>toString</code>, whether you like it or not! The best you can do is override <code>toString</code>. (Actually, Scala &ldquo;helpfully&rdquo; generates a nice <code>toString</code> override for you when you use case classes, hence the output of <code>Some(42)</code>.)</p>

<p>I consider this <em>global infection</em> a flaw in object-oriented languages that impose a set of methods on all objects whether you want them or not. <code>toString</code> is hardly the worst offending method, actually, but I&rsquo;ll save my complaints about others for later.</p>

<p>First step in cleaning up the code: make <code>toString</code> explicit:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  /** Only ever use a String to create a URL. */
  def makeUrl(id: String): String = s"http://service.com?id=$id"

  def main(args: Array[String]): Unit = {
    val id = findId("name")
    getUrl(makeUrl(id.toString))
  }
</code></pre>

<p>(Later in the post, I will discuss alternatives to this explicit <code>toString</code>.)</p>

<h3>Primitive obsession</h3>

<p>Another design smell was that of using</p>

<pre><code class="scala">type Id = Int
</code></pre>

<p>in the first place. This is a well-known lazy practice called <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?PrimitiveObsession">primitive obsession</a>. I know better than that.</p>

<p>The solution to primitive obsession is easy: create a new wrapper type. Hence, the original code, even before the possibly failing ID lookup, should have been</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  case class Id(id: Int)

  /**
    @param name User name to look up
    @return ID of user
    */
  def findId(name: String): Id =
    if (name == "name") {
      Id(42)
    } else {
      Id(0)
    }
</code></pre>

<p>Note that this still <em>would not</em> have solved the <code>toString</code> problem, since the output would simply have been <code>http://service.com?id=Some(Id(42))</code> or the dreaded <code>http://service.com?id=None</code>!</p>

<h3><code>toString</code> is a problematic concept anyway</h3>

<p>The real problem is one that transcends programming language design. (Later in this post I&rsquo;ll show languages that don&rsquo;t have <code>toString</code> but still easily allow a similar problem.)</p>

<p>The real problem is that strings are used for <em>multiple</em> purposes. Some are used just for debugging, showing an internal representation of data. Some are used for &ldquo;human&rdquo; reading. In fact, many languages distinguish between these two purposes: Lisp has <a href="http://www.lispworks.com/documentation/HyperSpec/Body/f_wr_pr.htm"><code>write</code>, <code>prin1</code>, <code>print</code>, <code>pprint</code></a>; Scheme has <a href="http://www.scheme.com/tspl3/io.html"><code>write</code> and <code>display</code></a>; Ruby has <a href="http://ruby-doc.org/core-2.0.0/Object.html"><code>to_s</code> and <code>to_str</code></a>; Python has <a href="http://docs.python.org/2/library/functions.html"><code>repr</code> and <code>str</code></a>.</p>

<p>One is often directed to override the &ldquo;human-oriented&rdquo; version of these mechanisms (implementing one&rsquo;s own special non-default format). In Java and Scala, that&rsquo;s <code>toString</code>. But this is precisely the problem. We are <em>encouraged</em> to abuse this built-in mechanism for getting a string from an object that is supposed to mean something in the <em>context of an application</em>. Yes, <code>Some(Id(42))</code> is a useful human-readable string, but it&rsquo;s not what I want to put into a URL for an ID parameter!</p>

<h4>Different names for different contexts</h4>

<p>Suppose you had a <code>Name</code> class, and it had fields such as <code>first</code> and <code>middle</code> and <code>last</code>. It&rsquo;s nonsensical to expect a single <code>toString</code> override to express all the different contexts in which you might want to get a single string from a full name. Sometimes you might want to generate <code>Franklin Chen</code>; other times, <code>Franklin Ming Chen</code>; other times, <code>Franklin M. Chen</code>; other times, <code>FMC</code>. The point is that there should really be a method for each of these. <code>toString</code> should be treated really as a debugging device.</p>

<p>Instead of piggybacking on <code>toString</code>, we should call a spade a spade, and define our own methods whose name is actually informative and tells us for what <em>purpose</em> we are asking for a string.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s refactor the code:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  // Wrapper class
  case class Id(id: Int) {
    // Special method for turning to URL string fragment
    def toUrlString = id.toString
  }

  /**
    @param name User name to look up
    @return Some(ID of user) if found, else None
    */
  def findId(name: String): Option[Id] =
    if (name == "name") {
      Some(Id(42))
    } else {
      None
    }

  /** Only ever use a String to create a URL. */
  def makeUrl(id: String): String = s"http://service.com?id=$id"

  /** Simulate making the Web request. */
  def getUrl(url: String): Unit = println(url)

  def main(args: Array[String]): Unit = {
    val id = findId("name")
    // Will not compile because Option[Id] does not have toUrlString
    //getUrl(makeUrl(id.toUrlString))
  }
</code></pre>

<p>Now the code that was creating a junk URL will no longer compile: <code>id</code> is of type <code>Option[Id]</code> but that type does <em>not</em> have a <code>toUrlString</code> method. Mission accomplished!</p>

<p>To fix the code to get it compile, we handle both the case in which the ID is not found and the case in which it is:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">    // Will not compile because Option[Id] does not have toUrlString
    //getUrl(makeUrl(id.toUrlString))

    id match {
      case None =&gt; println("No id found!")
      case Some(n) =&gt; getUrl(makeUrl(n.toUrlString))
    }
</code></pre>

<p>Simple!</p>

<h2>The final string gotcha (to be discussed later)</h2>

<p>You may have noticed that there is still primitive obsession in this sample code: URLs are presented as <code>String</code> for simplicity. In real life, I use builders such as <code>URIBuilder</code> and <code>HttpGet</code> (Java <a href="http://hc.apache.org/">Apache HttpComponents</a>) or more sophisticated Scala-specific libraries.</p>

<p>However, at some point, data has to be turned into strings: this simply is how the Web works. It is at that point where one has to watch out. I will discuss that boundary in another post. String injection attacks are precisely a result of being sloppy about crossing that boundary.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I gave a small taste of what the <code>toString</code> problem is about, and some initial steps toward solving it through better design even if the programming language encourages us to be sloppy.</p>

<p>In part 2 of this series, I will expand on different design choices even in the situation we just examined, especially in the face of continued evolution in which there are multiple domain classes to be turned into strings.</p>

<p>Finally, there actually are quite a few languages that don&rsquo;t have this particular <code>toString</code> problem, but some have analogues to a lesser degree. Part 3 of this series will discuss the different design choices in the languages or in the standard libraries or idioms. Examples will be drawn from C, C++, Haskell, Go, Standard ML, OCaml, Rust, and JavaScript.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
