<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: type classes | The Conscientious Programmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/categories/type-classes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-18T01:08:23-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Franklin Chen]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[franklinchen@franklinchen.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Understanding Clojure transducers through types]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2014/08/07/understanding-cloure-transducers-through-types/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-07T22:58:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2014/08/07/understanding-cloure-transducers-through-types</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, Rich Hickey published a blog post, <a href="http://blog.cognitect.com/blog/2014/8/6/transducers-are-coming">&ldquo;Transducers are Coming&rdquo;</a>, which attracted a lot of attention.</p>

<p>I have a confession to make, which I have made before: I find it very difficult to understand ideas or code not presented with <em>types</em>. So I decided that the only way I could possibly understand what &ldquo;transducers&rdquo; are would be to actually implement them in a typed language. I ended up doing so and am sharing my findings here.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Vague types in the original blog post</h2>

<p>Rich informally gave some type signatures in his blog post:</p>

<pre><code class="text">;;reducing function signature
whatever, input -&gt; whatever

;;transducer signature
(whatever, input -&gt; whatever) -&gt; (whatever, input -&gt; whatever)
</code></pre>

<p>This was, unfortunately, not very helpful. It is hard to make sense of this pseudo-notation for types. What is quantified over what? And what is bound to what? I&rsquo;ll explain later what I mean by these questions.</p>

<h2>First discussion thread I saw</h2>

<p>There was much tweeting online about transducers after Rich Hickey&rsquo;s initial announcement; the tweets did not help me, except for links posted to discussion elsewhere.</p>

<p>One of them was <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8143905">on Hacker News</a>. I browsed through it but found it mostly not useful. The problem was that although a lot of interesting Haskell code was thrown around, it tended to be <em>related</em> to transducers but not an <em>exact</em> translation of the concept. I already had my own intuitions about transducers being related to well-known types such as <a href="http://www.haskell.org/haskellwiki/Foldable_and_Traversable">foldables</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iteratee">iteratees</a>, <a href="https://lens.github.io/">lenses</a>, etc. That &ldquo;ordinary function composition&rdquo; was involved immediately suggested the connections, because function composition is huge in these existing Haskell libraries.</p>

<p>But what I wanted was to understand transducers <em>as they are</em>, before even thinking about generalizations and comparisons.</p>

<h3>What are the types?</h3>

<p>Rich Hickey <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8144385">informally offered some types</a> (which he said were &ldquo;a la Haskell&rdquo;) to try to help out:</p>

<pre><code class="text">    ;;reducing fn
    x-&gt;a-&gt;x

    ;;transducer fn
    (x-&gt;a-&gt;x)-&gt;(x-&gt;b-&gt;x)
</code></pre>

<p>OK, by using type variables <code>a</code>, <code>b</code>, and <code>x</code>, that indicates what is bound to what. The blog post should have used this notation rather than</p>

<pre><code class="text">;;transducer signature
(whatever, input -&gt; whatever) -&gt; (whatever, input -&gt; whatever)
</code></pre>

<h3>Sample Clojure code</h3>

<p>He also posted some sample Clojure code:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/b5aefa622180681e1c81.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>(require &#39;[clojure.core.async :as a])

(def xform (comp (map inc)
              (filter even?)
              (dedupe)
              (flatmap range)
              (partition-all 3)
              (partition-by #(&lt; (apply + %) 7))
              (flatmap flatten)
              (random-sample 1.0)
              (take-nth 1)
              (keep #(when (odd? %) (* % %)))
              (keep-indexed #(when (even? %1) (* %1 %2)))
              (replace {2 &quot;two&quot; 6 &quot;six&quot; 18 &quot;eighteen&quot;})
              (take 11)
              (take-while #(not= 300 %))
              (drop 1)
              (drop-while string?)
              (remove string?)))

(def data (vec (interleave (range 18) (range 20))))

;; lazily transform the data
(sequence xform data)
;; reduce with a transformation (no laziness)
(transduce xform + 0 data)
;;build one collection from a transformation of another, again no laziness
(into [] xform data)
;;create a recipe for a transformation, which can be subsequently sequenced, iterated or reduced
(iteration xform data)
;;transform everything that goes through a channel - same transducer stack!
(let [c (a/chan 1 xform)]
  (a/thread (a/onto-chan c data))
  (a/&lt;!! (a/into [] c)))</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<h2>Second discussion thread I saw</h2>

<p>Then today, I saw a discussion thread on Reddit, titled <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/haskell/comments/2cv6l4/clojures_transducers_are_perverse_lenses/">&ldquo;Clojure&rsquo;s Transducers are Perverse Lenses&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<h3>Actual runnable Haskell code</h3>

<p>Rich finally posted some actual <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/haskell/comments/2cv6l4/clojures_transducers_are_perverse_lenses/">type-checked, runnable Haskell code</a>!</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">-- Transducers in Haskell

mapping :: (a -&gt; b) -&gt; (r -&gt; b -&gt; r) -&gt; (r -&gt; a -&gt; r)
-- Original was (b -&gt; a) -&gt; (r -&gt; a -&gt; r) -&gt; (r -&gt; b -&gt; r)
-- but Michael O'Keefe in comment pointed out this is misleading
mapping f xf r a = xf r (f a)

filtering :: (a -&gt; Bool) -&gt; (r -&gt; a -&gt; r) -&gt; (r -&gt; a -&gt; r)
filtering p xf r a = if p a then xf r a else r

flatmapping :: (a -&gt; [b]) -&gt; (r -&gt; b -&gt; r) -&gt; (r -&gt; a -&gt; r)
flatmapping f xf r a = foldl xf r (f a)

-- for exposition only, yes, conj is gross for lazy lists
-- in Clojure conj and left folds dominate
conj xs x = xs ++ [x]
xlist xf = foldl (xf conj) []

-- build any old list function with its transducer, all the same way
xmap :: (a -&gt; b) -&gt; [a] -&gt; [b]
xmap f = xlist $ mapping f 

xfilter :: (a -&gt; Bool) -&gt; [a] -&gt; [a]
xfilter p = xlist $ filtering p

xflatmap :: (a -&gt; [b]) -&gt; [a] -&gt; [b]
xflatmap f = xlist $ flatmapping f

-- again, not interesting for lists, but the same transform 
-- can be put to use wherever there's a step fn

xform :: (r -&gt; Integer -&gt; r) -&gt; (r -&gt; Integer -&gt; r)
xform = mapping (+ 1) . filtering even . flatmapping (\x -&gt; [0 .. x])


print $ xlist xform [1..5]
-- [0,1,2,0,1,2,3,4,0,1,2,3,4,5,6]
</code></pre>

<p>After this post, I knew it would not take me long to figure out transducers.</p>

<h2>Refactoring his Haskell code</h2>

<p>Two things to notice about the original code:</p>

<ul>
<li>It has long, low-level function types rather than types that actually <em>name</em> the concepts being discussed (<em>reducers</em> and <em>transducers</em>).</li>
<li>It uses hardcoded list types <code>[a]</code>.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Type synonyms and higher-rank types</h3>

<p>Defining lots and lots of types (whether synonyms or <a href="http://www.haskell.org/haskellwiki/Newtype">newtypes</a> is standard practice when programming in a modern typed language. OK, so I defined a type synonym</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">-- Left reduce
type Reducer a r = r -&gt; a -&gt; r
</code></pre>

<p>But what about transducer? This is trickier.</p>

<p>An <em>invalid</em> attempt at a type would be</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">-- Illegal!
type Transducer a b = Reducer a r -&gt; Reducer b r
</code></pre>

<p>because the type variable <code>r</code> is not bound in the type definition. And it would be incorrect to just randomly add <code>r</code> on the left hand side as an extra parameter to the <code>Transducer</code> type, because in fact it is <em>critical</em> that a transducer <em>does not care</em> about the underlying reducer&rsquo;s return type <code>r</code>. How do we write the desired type?</p>

<p>It turns out you need <a href="http://www.haskell.org/haskellwiki/Rank-N_types">higher-rank types</a>. Rank-1 types are not sufficient; we need a rank-2 type to quantify <code>r</code>, to say that a transducer from <code>a</code> to <code>b</code> is a transformation that takes a reducer to a specific <code>r</code> and returns another reducer to the <em>same</em> <code>r</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">-- Here's where the rank-2 type is needed
type Transducer a b = forall r . Reducer a r -&gt; Reducer b r
</code></pre>

<p>Now we can see more clearly some <em>completely generic</em> ways to create a transducer:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">mapping :: (a -&gt; b) -&gt; Transducer b a
mapping f xf r a = xf r (f a)

filtering :: (a -&gt; Bool) -&gt; Transducer a a
filtering p xf r a = if p a then xf r a else r
</code></pre>

<h4>A bit of history</h4>

<p>Higher-rank types are a powerful technique for expressing &ldquo;hiding&rdquo; of unnecessary details about types going on somewhere. My first recollection of the real world use of rank-2 types is from 1994 (the year I started using Haskell, although I did not actually use it in my work as a software engineer until 1995), when I was excited to read a paper by John Launchbury and Simon Peyton Jones that solved, using a rank-2 type, a specific, important, practical problem, <a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.50.3299">&ldquo;Lazy Functional State Threads&rdquo;</a>; twenty years later, their <a href="http://hackage.haskell.org/package/base-4.7.0.1/docs/Control-Monad-ST.html">ST monad</a> is still part of the standard library!</p>

<h3>Introducing type classes</h3>

<p>Clojure uses <a href="http://clojure.org/protocols">protocols</a> as an abstraction mechanism, and the &ldquo;magic&rdquo; of transducers uses protocols. In Haskell, type classes are the major abstraction mechanism (this is true of Scala also).</p>

<p>So I abstracted away from the hardcoded list-oriented functions and values in Rich Hickey&rsquo;s Haskell code:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>foldl</code> abstracted to a <code>class Foldable</code></li>
<li><code>conj</code> and empty list <code>[]</code> abstracted to a <code>class Conjable</code></li>
</ul>


<pre><code class="haskell">-- Left fold
class Foldable f where
  fold :: Transducer a (f a)

class Conjable f where
  empty :: f a
  conj :: Reducer a (f a)
</code></pre>

<p>Note our reliance on transducing and reducing from one type <code>a</code> to another, <code>f a</code>.</p>

<h4><code>Foldable</code> constraint</h4>

<p>Unlike <code>mapping</code> and <code>filtering</code>, <code>flatmapping</code> is <em>not completely generic</em>, because it depends on something being <code>Foldable</code> (implementing a <code>fold</code>):</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">flatmapping :: Foldable f =&gt; (a -&gt; f b) -&gt; Transducer b a
flatmapping f xf r a = fold xf r (f a)
</code></pre>

<h4><code>Conjable</code> constraint</h4>

<p>Finally, here&rsquo;s the originally list-specific code that now depends only on <code>Foldable</code> and <code>Conjable</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">-- I changed Rich Hickey's code to be more general than just list
-- but accept anything Conjable
xlist :: (Foldable f, Conjable f) =&gt; Transducer b a -&gt; f a -&gt; f b
xlist xf = fold (xf conj) empty

-- build any old Foldable function with its transducer, all the same way
xmap :: (Foldable f, Conjable f) =&gt; (a -&gt; b) -&gt; f a -&gt; f b
xmap f = xlist $ mapping f 

xfilter :: (Foldable f, Conjable f) =&gt; (a -&gt; Bool) -&gt; f a -&gt; f a
xfilter p = xlist $ filtering p

xflatmap :: (Foldable f, Conjable f) =&gt; (a -&gt; f b) -&gt; f a -&gt; f b
xflatmap f = xlist $ flatmapping f
</code></pre>

<h3>List-specific stuff</h3>

<p>Here is the list-specific code:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">-- Stuff specialized to lists.
-- To use another type, just make it a Foldable and Conjable.
instance Foldable [] where
  fold = foldl

-- for exposition only, yes, conj is gross for lazy lists
-- in Clojure conj and left folds dominate
instance Conjable [] where
  empty = []
  conj xs x = xs ++ [x]

-- Note: the type does not say anything about Foldable or Conjable,
-- even though the implementation just happens to use a list!
xform :: Transducer Integer Integer
xform = mapping (+ 1) . filtering even . flatmapping (\x -&gt; [0 .. x])

-- Again, this can munge anything Foldable and Conjable, not just a list.
munge :: (Foldable f, Conjable f) =&gt; f Integer -&gt; f Integer
munge = xlist xform
</code></pre>

<p>Notice some very important properties of this code:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>xform</code> has a type that does not mention lists at all, even though it is implemented using a list and cannot compile without the list <code>instance</code> implementations.</li>
<li><code>munge</code> also does not mention lists, and can transform anything that is <code>Foldable</code> and <code>Conjable</code>.</li>
</ul>


<p>Example:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">-- munge a list
-- [0,1,2,0,1,2,3,4,0,1,2,3,4,5,6]
example1 :: [Integer]
example1 = munge [1..5]
</code></pre>

<h3>Implementing another type to illustrate the genericity of transducers</h3>

<p>To illustrate Rich Hickey&rsquo;s main point, I implemented instances of <code>Foldable</code> and <code>Conjable</code> for a standard Haskell <code>Vector</code> library as an alternate &ldquo;collection-like&rdquo; type.</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">-- For example using Vector instead of list
import qualified Data.Vector as V

-- Implement Foldable, Conjable type classes for Vector
instance Foldable V.Vector where
  fold = V.foldl

instance Conjable V.Vector where
  empty = V.empty
  conj = V.snoc
</code></pre>

<p>And we can run <code>munge</code> directly on a vector instead of a list, <em>without making any changes</em>:</p>

<pre><code class="haskell">-- return a vector rather than a list; note the fact that munge actually
-- internally uses a list
example2 :: V.Vector Integer
example2 = munge $ V.enumFromN 1 5
</code></pre>

<p>This is <em>code reuse</em> at its best.</p>

<p>Note that there is nothing that ties transducers to any concrete &ldquo;collection&rdquo; type. We could write instances of <code>Foldable</code> and <code>Conjable</code> for some kind of &ldquo;channel&rdquo; abstraction, for example, and instantaneously be able to munge data coming from it and to another. In fact, this is already what is done in the real world, where Haskell and Scala are used in production at places like Facebook and Twitter to efficiently handle large amounts of data.</p>

<h2>My code repository</h2>

<p>My complete code is available <a href="https://github.com/FranklinChen/clojure-transducers-in-haskell">on GitHub</a>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>It was pretty exciting to see the announcement of the transducers library for Clojure, because it represents a level of abstraction that I think has not been expressed much in the world of dynamically typed languages, although the techniques are two decades old in the Haskell community in a statically typed setting. And I hope that I was able to convey the sheer elegance of Haskell as a way to express interesting types with practical ramifications for abstraction and pluggability.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pittsburgh Scala Meetup: Implicits]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2014/02/13/pittsburgh-scala-meetup-implicits/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-13T21:45:59-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2014/02/13/pittsburgh-scala-meetup-implicits</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Scala-Meetup/">Pittsburgh Scala Meetup</a> met with Justin presenting on <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Scala-Meetup/events/146581402/">&ldquo;Implicits&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Implicits</h2>

<p>Implicits are a novel and fantastically important feature of Scala. I wish there were a comprehensive and concise single resource about them out there, but I don&rsquo;t actually know of one.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been doing stuff with implicits lately. Not long ago, I wrote a blog post that involved <a href="/blog/2013/12/26/tostring-considered-harmful-part-2/">using Scala implicits to avoid relying on the inherited Java <code>toString</code> method</a>. More recently, for this meetup I posted some code that I hoped someone would comment on, in which <a href="https://github.com/franklinchen/test-specs2-matchers">I used implicits to try to simplify a DSL</a>. I&rsquo;m not sure this is the right design choice, but it was an experiment.</p>

<h2>Presentation</h2>

<p>Around 7 of us showed up.</p>

<p>Justin did some live coding using the Scala Worksheet to demonstrate various uses of implicits.</p>

<p>One use is to define an &ldquo;implicit function&rdquo; that can convert of a value of one type to another. This can be overused badly, unfortunately.</p>

<p>Another is to define an &ldquo;implicit parameter&rdquo; for a function so that you don&rsquo;t have to explicitly pass a parameter to the function, if there is an implicit value in scope.</p>

<p>Scala 2.10 greatly improved implicits by encapsulating the &ldquo;conversion&rdquo; pattern by means of an &ldquo;implicit class&rdquo;. Strangely, Scala Worksheet seemed to get confused when we played around and defined an implicit class that also had an implicit parameter. This led to some interesting detective work as we examined the generated JVM byte code to figure out what was going on! I thought it was useful for us to dig into this level; often it is useful to understand what something compiles to in order to better understand and appreciate a high-level language construct.</p>

<p>Finally, we briefly discussed the type class pattern, which is arguably the most important use of implicits. This was too big a topic to get into here though.</p>

<h2>Resources</h2>

<p>I posted some good resources that have popped up on my radar on Scala implicits:</p>

<ul>
<li>A fine <a href="http://like-a-boss.net/2013/03/29/polymorphism-and-typeclasses-in-scala.html">tutorial on type classes in Scala</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://typelevel.org/blog/2014/01/18/implicitly_existential.html">Scary stuff with implicits</a> that I don&rsquo;t understand (yet).</li>
</ul>


<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Justin gave a nice introduction to implicits. I think the live coding and experimentation is a great way to involve people in code suggestions and discussion of what things mean and do. It was a fun time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[toString considered harmful, part 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/27/tostring-considered-harmful-part-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T22:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/27/tostring-considered-harmful-part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is part 3 of a series of articles, &ldquo;<code>toString</code> considered harmful&rdquo;.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Languages without the <code>toString</code> problem</h2>

<p>There actually are quite a few languages that don&rsquo;t have the <code>toString</code> problem, or at least have it to a lesser degree.</p>

<h3>C</h3>

<p>There is no friendly generic conversion to a string (uh, really just a pointer to a null-terminated chunk of <code>char</code>) in C. The closest thing is using the type-unsafe <code>printf</code> family of functions, but you have to do almost all the work if you have some complicated <code>struct</code> and want to turn it into a C string.</p>

<h3>C++</h3>

<p>C++ introduced iostreams, where f you follow certain conventions and overload <code>operator&lt;&lt;</code> for every domain class of interest, you can build up decent looking strings, without using inheritance.</p>

<p>Or you could do the object-oriented thing and set up a hierarchy with a <code>ToString</code> abstract base class. But C++ does not come with everything already inheriting from an <code>Object</code>.</p>

<h3>Haskell</h3>

<p>Haskell does not force a <code>toString</code> on everything, but provides a <a href="http://www.haskell.org/tutorial/stdclasses.html"><code>Show</code> type class</a> for convenience in the standard prelude. It is easy (and convenient for debugging) to just tack on <code>deriving Show</code> and then call <code>show</code> to convert stuff to a string. This means that one can get lazy and fall into the same design traps as mentioned in the very first code example above. Again, the solution is to refuse to abuse <code>show</code>, and to use a different name instead for converting something to a string for a particular purpose.</p>

<h3>Go</h3>

<p>Go was invented at Google as a modernized C. It does not have classes, but does have <a href="http://research.swtch.com/interfaces">dynamic interfaces</a>. All that is required for a user-defined type to satisfy an interface is to implement the method <code>String()</code> returning a <code>string</code>. Basically, this makes the type implement the interface <a href="http://golang.org/pkg/fmt/#Stringer">fmt.Stringer</a>. Again, if you don&rsquo;t implement <code>String() string</code> for your type, then you will get a compile-time error when trying to treat it as a string.</p>

<p>Superficially, this sounds like Haskell type classes, but it&rsquo;s much more limited, because Go does not have generics and Go is only single dispatch. Go&rsquo;s interfaces really implement a kind of structural subtyping.</p>

<h3>Standard ML</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.standardml.org/">Standard ML</a> does not have the <code>toString</code> problem. It does, by convention, supply a <code>toString</code> function in many modules in the <a href="http://www.standardml.org/Basis/">Standard ML Basis Library</a>, such as <a href="http://www.standardml.org/Basis/integer.html">Int</a> and <a href="http://www.standardml.org/Basis/real.html">Real</a> and <a href="http://www.standardml.org/Basis/bool.html">Bool</a>, but these are just conventions and do not participate in any kind of unified conversion to string. If you want to convert anything besides a primitive type to a string, you have to write the conversion function yourself.</p>

<p>Furthermore, Standard ML, as a rather opinionated and <a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/books/definition-standard-ml">&ldquo;purist&rdquo; language</a>, designed specifically for static simplicity, semantic minimalism, and <a href="http://mlton.org/">runtime efficiency</a>, does not believe in type classes, so there is no way to write a function that at runtime is generic over what can be turned into a string.</p>

<p>The best you can do is write something that is functorized, but then you have to apply it in a statically known context:</p>

<pre><code class="sml">signature TO_STRING =
  sig
    type t
    val toString : t -&gt; string
  end

functor DoStuff(ToString : TO_STRING) =
  struct
    fun doubleString (stuff: ToString.t) =
      let
        val s = ToString.toString stuff
      in
        s ^ s
      end
  end

structure MyStuff : TO_STRING =
  struct
    type t = int * bool
    fun toString (i, b) =
      "(" ^ Int.toString i ^ ", " ^ Bool.toString b ^ ")"
  end

structure DoMyStuff = DoStuff(MyStuff)
</code></pre>

<p>with</p>

<pre><code class="sml">DoMyStuff.doubleString (42, true)
(* result is the string "(42, true)(42, true)" *)
</code></pre>

<p>Since the Standard ML ecosystem is so minimalist, it&rsquo;s hard to fall into the <code>toString</code> trap, because you would have to set it all up yourself.</p>

<h3>OCaml</h3>

<p>OCaml, like Standard ML, does not provide a generic <code>toString</code> out of the box, but the OCaml ecosystem is much more practically oriented.</p>

<p>There is a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camlp4">pre-processor for OCaml</a> that can be used to generate convenient printers for types, <a href="https://github.com/ocsigen/deriving"><code>deriving</code></a>. There is also an S-expression based generator, <a href="http://realworldocaml.org/v1/en/html/data-serialization-with-s-expressions.html">Sexplib</a>. But these are mechanically generated, rather than part of something generic at runtime.</p>

<p>Of course, one could also use the <a href="http://caml.inria.fr/pub/docs/manual-ocaml-4.01/objectexamples.html">object-oriented part of OCaml</a> to make a generic &ldquo;to string&rdquo; hierarchy starting with a suitable interface:</p>

<pre><code class="ocaml">class type convert_to_string =
  object
    method to_string : string
  end
</code></pre>

<p>But I don&rsquo;t actually know many people who use the object-oriented features of OCaml!</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>An annoying bug I temporarily created in my code led me to take stock of the state of <code>toString</code> design choices in various programming languages, and also consider how we can better escape fragility in our code, independent of whatever language we are using.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[toString considered harmful, part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/26/tostring-considered-harmful-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-26T22:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/blog/2013/12/26/tostring-considered-harmful-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is part 2 of a series of articles, &ldquo;<code>toString</code> considered harmful&rdquo;. [Part 1] introduced the problem in the context of a common design flaw present in object-oriented languages, and proposed a simple workaround.</p>

<p>In part 2, we look at advanced ways to organize &ldquo;stringable&rdquo; data, using either an object-oriented or functional style. Examples are in Scala because it equally supports either style.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Object-oriented vs. functional</h2>

<p>The fix presented was in <em>object-oriented</em> style, adding a method <code>toUrlString</code> to a class. The other solution is the <em>functional</em> style, leaving the <code>Id</code> class alone, and writing an external function instead:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  case class Id(id: Int)

  def toUrlString(id: Id) = id.toString
</code></pre>

<p>with</p>

<pre><code class="scala">    id match {
      case None =&gt; println("No id found!")
      case Some(n) =&gt; getUrl(makeUrl(toUrlString(n)))
    }
</code></pre>

<p>There are advantages and disadvantages to either solution.</p>

<h2>More advanced OO</h2>

<p>It would be very natural, given a whole set of domain classes in addition to <code>Id</code>, to want all of them to have a <code>toUrlString</code>. Then the natural thing to do is to create a mini-universe (parallel to the <code>toString</code> universe) by creating a hierarchy:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  trait UrlString {
    def toUrlString: String
  }

  case class Id(id: Int) extends UrlString {
    override def toUrlString = id.toString
  }

  case class ...(...) extends UrlString {
    override def toUrlString = ...
  }
</code></pre>

<h2>Advanced string interpolation with OO</h2>

<p>In fact, Scala and other languages with advanced string interpolation facilities allow yet another refactoring by making sure that what gets into a URL isn&rsquo;t just an arbitrary string in the first place!</p>

<p>Below we define a string interpolator that only operates on objects of classes that implement the trait <code>UrlString</code>, and therefore does away with an explicit call to <code>toUrlString</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  implicit class UrlHelper(val sc: StringContext) extends AnyVal {
    def url(args: UrlString*): String = {
      val strings = sc.parts.iterator
      val expressions = args.iterator
      val buf = new StringBuffer(strings.next)
      while (strings.hasNext) {
        buf append expressions.next.toUrlString
        buf append strings.next
      }
      buf.toString
    }
  }

  /** Only ever use UrlString to create a URL. */
  def makeUrl(id: UrlString): String = url"http://service.com?id=$id"
</code></pre>

<p>with</p>

<pre><code class="scala">    id match {
      case None =&gt; println("No id found!")
      case Some(n) =&gt; getUrl(makeUrl(n))
    }
</code></pre>

<p>This may or may not be overengineering.</p>

<h2>Advanced string interpolation with FP</h2>

<p>The functional approach doesn&rsquo;t like inheritance in the domain classes. We can implement it with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Type_class">type classes</a> (a concept first pioneered in Haskell in the late 1980s) by means of implicits in Scala, in order to implement <code>toUrlString</code> outside of a class hierarchy but also allow it to be used in a constrained generic way. A full discussion of this is outside the scope of this post, but the basic point is that with type classes, one can write code that does <em>not</em> depend on an inheritance hierarchy. If you&rsquo;re used to monkey-patching in dynamic languages, think of it as compile-time monkey-patching.</p>

<pre><code class="scala">  // A type class
  trait UrlString[A] {
    def toUrlString(a: A): String
  }

  // Wrapper class
  case class Id(id: Int)

  // Implement the type class UrlString for Id
  implicit object IdToUrlString extends UrlString[Id] {
    override def toUrlString(a: Id) = a.id.toString
  }

  implicit class UrlHelper(val sc: StringContext) extends AnyVal {
    def url[A: UrlString](args: A*): String = {
      val strings = sc.parts.iterator
      val expressions = args.iterator
      val buf = new StringBuffer(strings.next)
      while (strings.hasNext) {
        buf append implicitly[UrlString[A]].toUrlString(expressions.next)
        buf append strings.next
      }
      buf.toString
    }
  }

  /** Anything "viewable" as UrlString can be used to create a URL. */
  def makeUrl[A: UrlString](id: A): String = url"http://service.com?id=$id"
</code></pre>

<h2>The final string gotcha</h2>

<p>You may have noticed that there is still primitive obsession in this sample code: URLs are presented as <code>String</code> for simplicity. In real life, I use builders such as <code>URIBuilder</code> and <code>HttpGet</code> (Java <a href="http://hc.apache.org/">Apache HttpComponents</a>) or more sophisticated Scala-specific libraries such as <a href="http://spray.io/">Spray</a>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I thought it would useful to compare an object-oriented and a functional approach to unifying data that share a domain-consistent notion of conversion to a string. Scala is a language that allows easy expression of both.</p>

<p>In part 3, we will look at languages that just don&rsquo;t have the <code>toString</code> problem at all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
